<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-02-17T10:34:01+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/</id><title type="html">Quagmire</title><subtitle>Stuff I find cool/useful</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Pragmatic Programmer</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/02/17/pragmatic-programmer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pragmatic Programmer" /><published>2019-02-17T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-02-17T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/02/17/pragmatic-programmer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/02/17/pragmatic-programmer.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;pragmatic-programmer&quot;&gt;Pragmatic Programmer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Pragmatic Programmer - from journeyman to master” is a book on programming
written by Andrew Hunt and David Thomas. This book can be found
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Pragmatic-Programmer-Journeyman-Master/dp/020161622X&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
IMO, every programmer who codes for living should read this in order to understand
how to convert requirements to specifications to a flexible and maintainable code.
One message that stands out from this book is “You shouldn’t be wedded to any
particular technology, but have a broad enough background and experience base to
allow you to choose good solutions in particular situations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;naming&quot;&gt;Naming&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use intention revealing names&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid ambiguous variable names&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use pronounceable names&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Class names must be nouns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Method names must be verbs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose a consistent style and stick to it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;comments&quot;&gt;Comments&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Comments Lie!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid them as much as possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t keep commented code. Delete it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;data-structures&quot;&gt;Data Structures&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t blindly add getters and setters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Objects and data structures are anti-symmetric!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid creating hybrid of these two!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;error-handling&quot;&gt;Error Handling&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use exceptions rather than error codes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide meaningful messages with the exceptions thrown&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create exception classes based on the needs of the caller&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tdd&quot;&gt;TDD&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Write tests first, code later!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Test code is as important as production code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When in doubt follow the above rule!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;classes&quot;&gt;Classes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should follow SRP&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should follow OCP&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should follow DIP&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When classes lose cohesion, split them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;systems&quot;&gt;Systems&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Construction of a system must be separated from its use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One such mechanism is Dependency Injection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use the simplest thing that can possibly work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;functions&quot;&gt;Functions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Must be small&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Must do only one thing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use descriptive names&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have less number of input arguments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have no side effects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to avoid output arguments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Always follow command-query-separation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prefer exceptions to returning error codes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t Repeat Yourself (DRY)!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;formatting&quot;&gt;Formatting&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small source files preferable over large ones&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use vertical blank lines for visual cues&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Concepts closely related must be vertically closer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is just like paragraphs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep all instance variables at one place&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep the lines short&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;boundaries&quot;&gt;Boundaries&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;User learning-tests to understand third party APIs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Isolate boundaries through wrapping them inside our own class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;emergence&quot;&gt;Emergence&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Four rules of simple design:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Runs all tests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contains no duplication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expresses programmer’s intent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minimum number of classes and methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;concurrency&quot;&gt;Concurrency&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to avoid sharing data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep the concurrent code separate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid using more than one method on shared object&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep your synchronized sections as small as possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Treat spurious failures as candidate threading issues&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get your non-threaded code working first&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is better when broken code fails as early as possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-notes" /><summary type="html">Pragmatic Programmer “Pragmatic Programmer - from journeyman to master” is a book on programming written by Andrew Hunt and David Thomas. This book can be found here. IMO, every programmer who codes for living should read this in order to understand how to convert requirements to specifications to a flexible and maintainable code. One message that stands out from this book is “You shouldn’t be wedded to any particular technology, but have a broad enough background and experience base to allow you to choose good solutions in particular situations.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Checklist Manifesto: How to get Things Right</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/02/01/checklist-manifesto.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Checklist Manifesto: How to get Things Right" /><published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/02/01/checklist-manifesto</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/02/01/checklist-manifesto.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-to-trust-in-a-post-truth-world&quot;&gt;What to trust in a ‘post-truth’ world&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Dr. Atul Gawande. This book can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Checklist-Manifesto-How-Things-Right/dp/0312430000&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
Dr. Atul shows the benefits of a simple checklist against the complexity of
our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three types of failures:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Task itself is impossible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;failure due to ignorance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;failure due to ineptitude&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;problem-of-extreme-complexity&quot;&gt;Problem of extreme complexity&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are living in a world of super specialization. Even then there are mistakes
committed due to extremely complex procedures and scenarios, especially in
medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-checklist&quot;&gt;The checklist&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our world/fields today have become too complex to be put into our memory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;example of WWII Boeing model 299 plane: Too complex for one pilot. But with a
simple checklist the pilots were able to fly without accident&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two ways one fails in a complex environment: failure to remember steps - its
easy to miss mundane steps when there are more pressing events at hand. Easy
to convince ourselves to skip a simple step&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;checklists are a way to discipline ourselves into following these steps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they also help in our memory recall especially while under pressure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;end-of-the-master-builder&quot;&gt;End of the master builder&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checklists are a cognitive net against our inherent flaws in memory, attention
and thoroughness. 3 types of problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;simple: Like preparing a dish. Once a recipe is prepared that’s good enough&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;complicated: Like building rocket. Can be broken down into series of simple
problems. But there are unforeseen issues even for the experienced.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;complex: Like raising a child. Experience in raising one’s child well may not
guarantee success with another. There’s no recipe!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;master builder era is long gone. The complexity in today’s world is too much
for one guy to manage and track. The idea is to have experts in multiple
sub-specializations manage individual problems. But the crucial aspect is
that those experts need to get together to resolve any unexpected scenarios
or issues that span across multiple specializations. Man is fallible not men
less so! Fine example to this is the construction industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-idea&quot;&gt;The idea&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case of routine tasks and problems, we need a central authority who dictates
what needs to be done to their subordinates. In case of complex, unforeseen
circumstances, this power needs to be as far away from the center as possible.
Best example was 2005’s Katrina hurricane. Where government wasn’t still sure
who should provide help to stranded citizens, Walmart had supplied loads of help
already. This worked because Walmart decentralized the power away from center to
the local employees in wake of this incident. Under very complex scenarios
decentralization of power is the right approach. Under cases of extreme
complexity, which is behind anyone persons’ capacity, we need to decentralize
power and distribute it to respective front-lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-first-try&quot;&gt;The first try&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author recounts his experience while consulting for WHO regarding surgical
safety procedures world wide. Describes various hospitals trying to implement
checklists during surgery. And the importance of communication between the OR
group. The author tries to give such a checklist a try in his own hospital. Also
mentions a peculiar (yet intuitive) study where just by knowing the names of the
members in a group increased the communication in it. But because of ambiguities
and the length of the checklist, they had to stop using it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-checklist-factory&quot;&gt;The checklist factory&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 2 kinds of checklists:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bad ones - very long, detailed, treat people as dumb and list out every steps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;good ones - very short and precise, only list the most critical steps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But checklists can’t make people to follow them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;READ-DO checklist - people read items off the checklist, execute them and
then tick them off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DO-CONFIRM checklist - everyone executes a few steps from their memory and
then pauses to confirm whether all items from the list have been executed or
not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good checklist typically contains about 5 to 9 items. Most importantly the
checklist should be tested out in real world, at least once, before deploying it
widely!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-test&quot;&gt;The test&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping the list minimal is the biggest challenge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prune too many items, checklist could be too short to be effective in
preventing errors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;keep too many items, people hate to follow long lists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a delicate balance between brevity and effectiveness&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hero-in-the-age-of-checklists&quot;&gt;Hero in the age of checklists&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its just not about ticking-off items in checklist, it is about teamwork. Even
these checklists have found to be very useful in other fields like investing.
But very few have become the fan of checklists, despite their proven checklists!
We still think that people who follow their intuition are heroes and are real
men!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fear people have on checklists is rigidity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they think checklists will make them mindless automatons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;but in reality its the opposite!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;checklists take the routine (but important) stuffs off the brain’s working
memory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thus checklists will enable us in our fields&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heroes in today’s world are those who&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;know when to improvise and when not to&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;understand the importance of teamwork&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;know how to work in today’s complex environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checklists must aid, not hinder. We are meant to be for excitement and novelty.
Never to give attention to details and be disciplined. That’s where checklists
come to help us. Under the complexity of today’s world we have nothing else left
but to try checklists!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-save&quot;&gt;The save&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting story of an operation where the author accidentally tore the
patient’s vena-cava. But due to checklist they followed and worked as a team
they were able to atleast save the patient.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-notes" /><summary type="html">What to trust in a ‘post-truth’ world By Dr. Atul Gawande. This book can be found here. Dr. Atul shows the benefits of a simple checklist against the complexity of our lives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What to trust in a ‘post-truth’ world</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/28/what-to-trust-in-a-post-truth-world.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What to trust in a 'post-truth' world" /><published>2019-01-28T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-28T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/28/what-to-trust-in-a-post-truth-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/28/what-to-trust-in-a-post-truth-world.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-to-trust-in-a-post-truth-world&quot;&gt;What to trust in a ‘post-truth’ world&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Alex Edmonds. The recorded TED talk can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/alex_edmans_what_to_trust_in_a_post_truth_world/up-next&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
Alex talks about how confirmation bias could lead us astray in the current
world. He then provides a very compelling argument, urging us to consider data
and evidence very consciously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Confirmation bias - we accept stories that match our beliefs and reject those
that don’t. This is especially true in politics, business and health.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need to check if the data supports the theory, but instead we end up
checking of the data is consistent with the theory!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This consistency is alone not sufficient, because the same data could also be
consistent with the rival theory! (Due to confirmation bias, we’ll never
check for this)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Because of this bias we also accept a fact as data. And also accept data as
evidence, even if it consistent with rival theories.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data is a collection of facts. Evidence is the data that supports one theory
while ruling our others.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A story is not fact, because it may not be true.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A fact is not data, because it might not be representative.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data is not evidence, because it might be consistent with rival theories.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Actively seek out for rival points.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Play devil’s advocate with your decisions/theories.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pause before sharing anything!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only if it’s true, it can be a fact. Only if it’s representative, it can be
data. Only if it’s supportive, can it be evidence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="ted-talks" /><summary type="html">What to trust in a ‘post-truth’ world By Alex Edmonds. The recorded TED talk can be found here. Alex talks about how confirmation bias could lead us astray in the current world. He then provides a very compelling argument, urging us to consider data and evidence very consciously.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Teditor v1.0.0</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/26/teditor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Teditor v1.0.0" /><published>2019-01-26T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-26T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/26/teditor</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/26/teditor.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;teditor-v100&quot;&gt;Teditor v1.0.0!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2018/06/24/teditor.html&quot;&gt;an old post&lt;/a&gt; of
mine, I had announced Teditor, a terminal based editor completely written in
C++. Today, I’m glad to announce the release of its next version: v1.0.0. It
can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/teju85/teditor/releases/tag/1.0.0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;changelog&quot;&gt;Changelog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changes/features in this release:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Completely revamped command interface, so that users don’t have explicitly
encode undo/redo commands. This makes writing of commands/extensions much
easier.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every new command can be made to self-document and now there’s a help command
to query just that!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fixes to many bugs in editing commands, especially with active regions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="teditor" /><summary type="html">Teditor v1.0.0! In an old post of mine, I had announced Teditor, a terminal based editor completely written in C++. Today, I’m glad to announce the release of its next version: v1.0.0. It can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Design Principles and Design Patterns</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/26/design-patterns.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Design Principles and Design Patterns" /><published>2019-01-26T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-26T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/26/design-patterns</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/26/design-patterns.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-book&quot;&gt;The Book&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a really concise article/chapter on software design principles and
patterns by Robert C. Martin (commonly called Uncle Bob). The pdf version of
this book/chapter is available
&lt;a href=&quot;https://fi.ort.edu.uy/innovaportal/file/2032/1/design_principles.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;software arch is multi-tiered
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;At the highest level, there are the architecture patterns that define the
overall shape and structure of software applications.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Down a level is the architecture that is specifically related to the purpose
of the software application.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Yet another level down resides the architecture of the modules and their
interconnections. This is the domain of design patterns, packages,
components, and classes.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;four symptoms of rotting design: rigidity, fragility, immobility, and
viscosity.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;rigidity: tendency for the sw to be difficult to change&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;fragility: tendency of sw to break at many places even on a simple change&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;immobility: inability to reuse parts of other or the same project&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;viscosity of design: when design preserving solutions are harder to
implement than hacks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;viscosity of environment: development environment is inefficient&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reasons for sw rot
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;changing reqs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;bad dependency management&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OCP: open closed principle
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A module should be open for extension but closed for modification&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the most important rule of sw design&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;abstraction is the key to OCP&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;achieved through runtime and static polymorphism&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you don’t have to change working code, you aren’t likely to break it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;LSP: liskov substitution principle
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Subclasses should be substitutable for their base classes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;best paradox for this is circle/ellipse dillema
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;designing circle to inherit from ellipse is fine&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;but users of this code will ruin everything when one wants to pass
ellipse-like args to a circle object! (think about foci)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;thus the contract of base class must be obeyed by the child class&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;contract of a method consists of precondition and postcondtion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;restating LSP in terms of contracts
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;derived class is substitutable for its base class if:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Its preconditions are no stronger than the base class method.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Its postconditions are no weaker than the base class method.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;in other words, derived methods should expect no more and provide no less.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;violations of LSP are latent violations of OCP&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DIP: dependency inversion principle
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Depend upon Abstractions. Do not depend upon concretions.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If the OCP states the goal of OO architecture, the DIP states the primary
mechanism.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;No dependency should target a concrete class.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;concrete things change alot, abstract things change much less frequently&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;abstractions are “hinge points”, they represent the places where the design
can bend or be extended, without themselves being modified (OCP)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ISP: interface segregation principle. Many client specific interfaces are
better than one general purpose interface&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PCP: package cohesion principles
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;REP: release reuse equivalency principle
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;The granule of reuse is the granule of release.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;CCP: common closure principle
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Classes that change together, belong together.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;CRP: common reuse principle
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Classes that aren’t reused together should not be grouped together.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;these three principles are mutually exclusive. All of them cannot be
simultaneously satisfied&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PCP: package coupling principles
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ADP: acyclic dependencies principle
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;The dependencies betwen packages must not form cycles&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Cycles can be broken in two ways. The first involves creating a new
package, and the second makes use of the DIP and ISP&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Interfaces are very often included in the package that uses them, rather
than in the package that implements them.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SDP: stable dependencies principle
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Depend in the direction of stability.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;package stability measurement
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Ca = Afferent Coupling. The number of classes outside the package that
depend upon classes inside the package. (i.e. incoming dependencies)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Ce = Efferent Coupling. The number of classes outside the package that
classes inside the package depend upon. (i.e. outgoing dependencies)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;I = instability = Ce/(Ca+Ce)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Depend upon packages whose I metric is lower than yours&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SAP: stable abstractions principle
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stable packages should be abstract packages.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;compose application from instable packages that are easy to change, and
stable packages that are easy to extend.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;abstractness metric:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Nc = Number of classes in the package.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Na = Number of abstract classes in the package. Remember, an abstract
class is a class with at least one pure interface, and cannot be instantiated.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;A Abstractness = Na / Nc&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I should increase as A decreases&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two zones in the IA graph
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;upper right corner = zone of uselessness = only abstract classes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;lower left corner = zone of pain = lots of dependencies = only concrete
classes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;maximizing distance between these two zones gives us a line called main
sequence&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ideally our packages should sit on this line&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;distance metric
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;D = Distance from main sequence = |A+I-1|/sqrt(2). This ranges
from [0,~0.707].&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;D’ = Normalized Distance = |A+I-1|. This metric is much more convenient than
D since it ranges from [0,1]. Zero indicates that the package is directly on
the main sequence. One indicates that the package is as far away as possible
from the main sequence.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;design patterns = repeating structures of design and architecture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;abstract server: when client depends directly on server DIP is violated. Thus
create an interface which client uses but server implements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adapter: delegator of methods from an abstract interface to the third party
server implementation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;observer: when changes in one object needs to be informed to another without
each knowing much about the other&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bridge: base and child classes are tightly coupled. This creates a strong
separation between interface and implementation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;abstract factory: DIP strongly recommends that modules not depend upon
concrete classes. However, in order ot create an instance of a class, you must
depend upon the concrete class. This allows that dependency upon the concrete
class to exist in one, and only one, place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-notes" /><summary type="html">The Book This is a really concise article/chapter on software design principles and patterns by Robert C. Martin (commonly called Uncle Bob). The pdf version of this book/chapter is available here</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Man’s search for meaning</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/23/mans-search-for-meaning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Man's search for meaning" /><published>2019-01-23T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-23T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/23/mans-search-for-meaning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/23/mans-search-for-meaning.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-book&quot;&gt;The Book&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a phenomenal autobiographical account of Dr. Victor Frankl’s horrific
experience in concentration camps and his search of meaning for life amongst it.
The book is available
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Mans-Search-Meaning-Viktor-Frankl/dp/080701429X&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;part-1---experiences-in-concentration-camps&quot;&gt;Part 1 - Experiences in concentration camps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Autobiographical account of author’s horrific experiences in concentration camps
during the Holocaust. By taking the success of this book as an example he says
that we shouldn’t chase success, but to completely forget about it and continue
to do what we love the most. This precisely will be the reason success will
follow us one day. He describes the life at these camps to be a constant
struggle for food and survival, constant struggle against being becoming a
Moslem (an inmate who can no more work), for those Moslems would be gassed to
death. He examines three phases of any inmate in these camps: period following
his admission, period where he is well entrenched in camp’s routine and period
following his release. He goes onto describe his account of each of these phases
very vividly in this part. Thus, this part is a much needed background for the
next coming parts of this book!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase1 is almost always characterized by shock. It also comes with a ‘delusion
of reprieve’ (a child like optimism where one thinks he might fare well in
prison).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase2 is relative apathy where one achieves kind of an emotional death. This
apathy would have been caused due to the horrors in the camp against fellow
inmates. It was a necessary way of self-defence, as life there was uncertain.
But no matter what the circumstances (beyond our control!) have robbed us of,
they can’t rob a man of one thing - the freedom to choose how to act in a given
scenario. Frankl argues that no matter how dire are circumstances, one must not
loose faith in one’s future and should have some gaol for their lives. ‘For a
man who knows the Why to live for can bear almost any How’ (quoting Nietzel).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phase3 is hte psyche of the inmates after their release. Most take a long time
to be brought back to the mainstream of society. Initial few days were all about
de-personalization - disbelief about their dreams to have turned true. Some
people with primitive nature became ever more aggressive and ruthless after
their release. People also suffered from bitterness due to their home town folks
unable to acknowledge their suffering. They were also disillusioned in the sense
that they had thought after all these sufferings there’d be no more of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;part-2---logotherapy-in-a-nutshell&quot;&gt;Part 2 - Logotherapy in a nutshell&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logos in greek means meaning. As opposed to Freudean ‘will to pleasure’ and
Adlerian ‘will to power’ psychoanalytical methods, logotheraphy deals with the
‘will to meaning’. A man’s search for meaning for his life is the primary
motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not every conflict in us is neurotic and needs psychoanalysis. We must not
strive towards a tensionless mind, for mind is always in tension between what
has been achieved by that man so far and what still needs to be achieved (aka
neuro-dynamics).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Existential vaccum - total lack of awareness of meaning for one’s life. This is
very wide spread in our generation because of progressive automation and it
causing too much leisure on people’s hands. It almost always manifests itself in
a state of boredom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meaning of life is very unique to a person. Thus, in order to find this out, one
needs to reverse the thought process and ask what is being asked of oneself in
their life, that which he alone is responsible for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can realize the meaning of our lives via: doing a work, experiencing someone
or something and attitude we take towards difficult times or suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logos is deeper than logic. Everyone has the freedom to choose his actions or
responses to the circumstances we face daily. However, this freedom shouldn’t
lead to arbitrariness, but to responsibleness. We have people who act as swines
while others act as saints. Such mix of people are found in all races of
humanity. Man has both these potentialities and what he becomes is more based on
his choice than on circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;part-3---the-case-for-tragic-optimism&quot;&gt;Part 3 - The case for tragic optimism&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tragic optimism - being optimistic even while facing the trafic triads: pain,
guilt and death. And optimism, like happiness, cannot be pursued but ensued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Existential vaccum also results in depression, aggression and addition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suffering is not the only way to finding meaning, for if it is avoidable, the
smart thing to do is to remove its cause. Unnecessary suffering is masochistic
not herioc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live as if you’re living for the second time and had acted as wrongly as you’re
about to act now. Because, since Auschwitz, we know what man is capable of and
since Nagashima, we know what is at stake!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-notes" /><summary type="html">The Book This is a phenomenal autobiographical account of Dr. Victor Frankl’s horrific experience in concentration camps and his search of meaning for life amongst it. The book is available here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to be a leader</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/15/how-to-be-a-leader.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to be a leader" /><published>2019-01-15T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/15/how-to-be-a-leader</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/15/how-to-be-a-leader.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-book&quot;&gt;The Book&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book is a collection of 50 sayings from the nine-volumes of
&lt;em&gt;Complete works of Swami Vivekananda&lt;/em&gt;. The book is available
&lt;a href=&quot;https://istore.chennaimath.org/product/how-to-be-a-leader/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few of the sayings that I liked the most from this booklet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Followers will only follow those leaders who are ready to give up their life
for the cause.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you can’t learn to obey, you cannot lead.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Great things are only done through great sacrifices.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Know that talking ill of others in private is a sin.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is criticizing each other that is the root of all mischief.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-notes" /><summary type="html">The Book This book is a collection of 50 sayings from the nine-volumes of Complete works of Swami Vivekananda. The book is available here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Essentials of Hinduism</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/01/essentials-of-hinduism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Essentials of Hinduism" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/01/essentials-of-hinduism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/01/01/essentials-of-hinduism.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-book&quot;&gt;The Book&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book is a collection of ideas about Hinduism from Swami Vivekananda, by
Swami Tattwavidananda. The book is available
&lt;a href=&quot;https://istore.chennaimath.org/product/essentials-of-hinduism/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;origin-of-the-word-hindu&quot;&gt;Origin of the word Hindu&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a term started by Persians to call the people who lived on the other side
of the Indus river. Vaidikas (followers of veda) or Vedantists (followers of
vedanta) is a more apt word for a Hindu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-vedas&quot;&gt;The vedas&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vedas are the knowledge of God himself. As such, they don’t have a beginning nor
an end. Rishis (the seer of thought or knowledge), were mere discoverers of this
knowledge that already existed in the universe. Vedas are divided into 2 parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Karma Kanda - the duties of student, man, householder and recluse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jnana Kanda - Vedanta or the end of Vedas, the spiritual portion. It comprises
of Upanishads.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;different-schools-of-thought&quot;&gt;Different Schools of Thought&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 2 pre-dominant interpretations of Vedanta:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dualists - Dwaita philosophy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monists - Adwaita philosophy
These mainly differ in the way they relate between God, Soul and Nature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;vedanta-is-not-the-adwaita-system-only&quot;&gt;Vedanta is not the Adwaita system only&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every sect is mainly an interpretation of the 3 Prasthana’s:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Upanishads - Revelations - Shruti’s&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sutras - Vyasa Sutras - a consummation of all preceding philosophies!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gita - the divine commentary of the Vedanta itself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;smritis&quot;&gt;Smriti’s&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Books written by sages to lead us on how to live our lives, corresponding to
the state of that society of that time. However, they are subordinate to the
Vedanta, in the sense that if they contradict anything in Vedanta, they are
supposed to be rejected. Because Vedanta is built upon eternal principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;puranas-and-tantras&quot;&gt;Puranas and Tantras&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Puranas are simplified version of Vedas to be amenable towards common people.
They talk about the same eternal principles in forms of stories. Tantras were
an attempt to revive the sacrificial ideas found in Karma Kanda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;why-different-sects&quot;&gt;Why different sects?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though there so many sects, the book goes onto concentrate on the
intersection of all these, which every Hindu must believe&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;theory-of-creation&quot;&gt;Theory of creation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This world has not been created by God on one fine day. It is, instead,
continually undergoing through the process of creation and disintegration. Thus,
there is no beginning or end to this Nature (aka Prakriti).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;brahman&quot;&gt;Brahman&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Almighty, benevolent eternal being who creates and sustains this universe is
Brahman. But the disparity/partiality we see in our worlds is mainly due to the
fault of ours, for it is not the fault in clouds, but the properties of the land
who receives their rains, to grow good crops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;law-of-karma&quot;&gt;Law of Karma&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A child is not born out of gift from nature, but born due to his infinite past.
So, the differentiation we see around us is caused by us and only us. We are the
cause and the effect of our own deeds. If we can be sad, we could be happy too.
If we are impure, we can become pure too. This is the law of Karma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-soul&quot;&gt;The Soul&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We cannot understand God without the understanding of Soul (Atman). Every form
of life has a soul, however big or small. Atman goes through the process of
birth and death of the body, accompanied by the mind (Sukshma Sharira). The
ultimate goal, hence, should not be heaven, but freedom (Mukti) from this cycle
into an Eternal Bliss (Aananda). Just like we are distracted by power, position
and money in this materialistic world, we will be distracted by similar such
situations even in heaven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mukti-or-freedom&quot;&gt;Mukti or Freedom&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ignorance is the cause for all bondage. Knowledge is the means to break this
bondage. This knowledge is attained through Bhakti, love towards God and his
creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;life-after-death&quot;&gt;Life after Death&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no permanent heaven without the realization of God. Also, anything
with name and form has a beginning and end in time. Likewise heavens too are
temporary and we should give up on them and instead pursue Eternal Bliss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;universalism&quot;&gt;Universalism&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God is like the same light coming in different colors out of the prism. He is
like the string unifying all the pearls (religions, beliefs, etc) together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;image-worship&quot;&gt;Image worship&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rose called by any other name still smells sweet. Different forms of worship of
God, under different names, images and idols are all but an effort by our minds
to try to realize the divine. This is because material image calls upon the
mental idea and vice-versa. Hence, none of these forms of worship be called sin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;guru&quot;&gt;Guru&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every soul is destined to be perfect. But the trigger to become perfect only
comes from another soul. We could learn about spirituality from infinite books.
Those will only tell us how to speak spiritualism, but do not help when it comes
to its practice. This only happens with the interaction and guidance of another
soul, called Guru (the teacher).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;divine-incarnation&quot;&gt;Divine incarnation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Divine incarnations are the highest manifestations of God through a man. They
are the teachers of all teachers. These are the ones we are bound to workship.
Being humans, we cannot see God and worship Him as anything other than a human.
There are only two kinds of people who do not worship God as another human:
an ignorant fellow and a free soul (Jeevanmukta) who has expanded his knowledge
to understand that God is everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;yoga---the-means&quot;&gt;Yoga - The means&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoga (union) is the union between the following four directions, that which
applies to all sectors of people in a community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To the worker, between man and the whole of humanity - Karma Yoga&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To the mystic, between his lower and higher self - Raja Yoga&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To the lover, between himself and the God - Bhakti Yoga&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To the philosopher, the union of all existence - Jnana Yoga
An ideal religion is the one that finds harmony among all these 4 directions.
A Yogi is one who practices in any of these forms of Yoga.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;raja-yoga&quot;&gt;Raja Yoga&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 3 sorts of instruments of knowledge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intuition - basest of all the instruments, found in all animals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reason - found in men. But even this has limitations when it comes to
acquiring knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inspiration - our reasoning functions only within the realm of our own
consciouness. Inspiration is the third instrument that can helps us gain
knowledge beyond the limited realm of our reasoning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note, however, that all these 3 instruments will never contradict each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concentration is the main workhorse behind every deed of a man. It is a way of
trying to bring to focus, our galloping mind, into the very act one is doing.
Raja Yoga deals with the challenges of trying to get our minds to concentrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;karma-yoga&quot;&gt;Karma Yoga&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karma Yoga deals with the aspect of attaining God through work. Greater part of
out energies are spent dealing with misery, misery which arises through our
expectation of something in return for the work we have done, for the help we
did for another human being. A Karma Yogi is deattached from his work, he only
gives and cares less in return, thereby, he is free from the pains of misery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bhakti-yoga&quot;&gt;Bhakti Yoga&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bhakti Yoga teaches us how to love God. It shows us God is there in every form
of love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;jnana-yoga&quot;&gt;Jnana Yoga&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jnana Yoga teaches us that every life is a manifestation of God Himself. It
shows us the real unity of being, that each one of us is the Lord Himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-goal&quot;&gt;The Goal&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these forms of Yogas must not only be studied, but most importantly carried
out in practice. They must be listened to, mulled over, reasoned with, meditated
upon and practised, until they become part of us. After all, religion is all
about realization, not just ideals and theories.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-notes" /><summary type="html">The Book This book is a collection of ideas about Hinduism from Swami Vivekananda, by Swami Tattwavidananda. The book is available here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">You are not so smart</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2018/11/25/youre-not-so-smart.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You are not so smart" /><published>2018-11-25T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-11-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2018/11/25/youre-not-so-smart</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2018/11/25/youre-not-so-smart.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-book&quot;&gt;The Book&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book, written by David McRaney, is available
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/You-Are-Not-So-Smart/dp/1592407366&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this book David describes all our irrational behavior under the lens of
psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You are a rational logical being who sees the world as it really is.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You are as deluded as the rest of us, but that’s OK, it keeps you sane.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Priming
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You know you are being influenced and how it is affecting your behavior&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You are unaware of the constant nudging you receive from ideas formed in your unconscious mind.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Confabulation
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You know when you’re lying to yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You’re often ignorant of your motivations and created fictional narratives to explain your decisions, emotions and history without realizing it.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Confirmation Bias
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Your opinions are the result of years of rational, objective analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Your opinions are the result of years of paying attention to information that confirmed what you believed, while ignoring information that challenged your preconceived notions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hindsight Bias
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;After you learn something new, you remember how you were once ignorant or wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You often look back on the things you’ve just learned and assume you knew them or believed them all along.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Texas Sharpshooter Fallacy
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You take randomness into account when determining cause and effect.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You tend to ignore random chance when the results seem meaningful or when you want a random event to have a meaningful cause.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Procrastination
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You procrastinate because you are lazy and can’t manage your time well.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Procrastination is fueled by weakness in the face of impulse and a failure to think about thinking.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Normalcy Bias
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Your fight-or-flight instincts kick in and you panic when disaster strikes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You often become abnormally calm and pretend everything is normal in a crisis.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introspection
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You know why you like the things you like and feel the way you feel.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The origin of certain emotional states is unavailable to you, and when pressed to explain them, you will just make something up.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Availability Heuristic
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;With the advent of mass media, you understand how the world works based on statistics and facts culled from many examples.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You are far more likely to believe something is commonplace if you can find just one example of it, and you are far less likely to believe in something you’ve never seen or heard of before.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Bystander Effect
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When someone is hurt, people rush to their aid.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The more people who witness a person in distress, the less likely it is that any one person will help.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Dunning-Kruger Effect
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You can predict how well you would perform in any situation.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You are generally pretty bad at estimating your competence and the difficulty of complex tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apophenia
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Some coincidences are so miraculous, they must have meaning.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Coincidences are a routine part of life, even the seemingly miraculous ones. Any meaning applied to them comes from your mind.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brand Loyalty
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You prefer the things you own over the things you don’t because you made rational choices when you brought them.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You prefer the things you own because you rationalize your past choices to protect your sense of self.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Argument from Authority
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You are more concerned with the validity of information than the person delivering it.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The status and credentials of an individual greatly influence your perception of that individual’s message.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Argument from Ignorance
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When you can’t explain something, you focus on what you can prove.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When you are unsure of something, you are more likely to accept strange explanations.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Straw Man Fallacy
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When you argue, you try to stick to the facts.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In any argument, anger will tempt you to reframe your opponent’s position.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Ad Hominem Fallacy
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you can’t trust someone, you should ignore that person’s claims.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What someone says and why they say it should be judged separately.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Just-World Fallacy
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;People who are losing at the game of life must have done something to deserve it.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The beneficiaries of good fortune often do nothing to earn it, and bad people often get away with their actions without consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Public Goods Game
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;We could create a system with no regulations where everyone would contribute to the good of society, everyone would benefit, and everyone would be happy.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Without some form of regulation, slackers and cheaters will crash economic systems because people don’t want to feel like suckers.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Ultimatum Game
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You choose to accept or refuse an offer based on logic.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When it comes to making a deal, you base your decision on your status.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Subjective Validation
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You are skeptical of generalities.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You are prone to believing vague statements and predictions are true, especially if they are positive and address you personally.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cult Indoctrination
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You are too smart to join a cult.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cults are populated by people just like you.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Groupthink
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Problems are easier to solve when a group of people get together to discuss solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The desire to reach consensus and avoid confrontation hinders progress.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supernormal Releasers
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Men who have sex with RealDolls are insane, and women who marry eighty-year-old billionaires are gold diggers.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The RealDoll and rich old sugar daddies are both supernormal releasers.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Affect Heuristic
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You calculate what is risky or rewarding and always choose to maximize gains while minimizing losses.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You depend on emotions to tell you if something is good or bad, greatly overestimate rewards, and tend to stick to your first impressions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dunbar’s Number
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;There is a Rolodex in your mind with the names and faces of everyone you’ve ever known.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You can maintain relationships and keep up with only around 150 people at once.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Selling Out
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Both consumerism and capitalism are sustained by corporations and advertising.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Both consumerism and capitalism are driven by competition among consumers for status.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Self-Serving Bias
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You evaluate yourself based on past successes and defeats.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You excuse your failures and see yourself as more successful, more intelligent, and more skilled than you are.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Spotlight Effect
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When you are around others, you feel as if everyone is noticing every aspect of your appearance and behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;People devote little attention to you unless prompted to.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Third Person Effect
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You believe your opinions and decisions are based on experience and facts, while those who disagree with you are falling for the lies and propaganda of sources you don’t trust.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Everyone believes the people they disagree with are gullible, and everyone thinks they are far less susceptible to persuasion than they truly are.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Catharsis
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Venting your anger is an effective way to reduce stress and prevent lashing out at friends and family.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Venting increases aggressive behavior over time.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Misinformation Effect
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Memories are played back like recordings.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Memories are constructed anew each time from whatever information is currently available, which makes them highly permeable to influences from the present.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conformity
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You are a strong individual who doesn’t conform unless forced to.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It takes a little more than an authority figure or social pressure to get you to obey, because conformity is a survival instinct.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extinction Burst
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you stop engaging in a bad habit, the habit will gradually diminish until it disappears from your life.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Any time you quit something cold turkey, your brain will make a last-ditch effort to return you to your habit.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social Loafing
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When you are joined by others in a task, you work harder and become more accomplished.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Once part of a group, you tend to put in less effort because you know your work will be pooled together with others’.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Illusion of Transparency
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When your emotions run high, people can look at you and tell what you are thinking and feeling.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Your subjective experience is not observable, and you overestimate how much you telegraph your inner thoughts and emotions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learned Helplessness
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you are in a bad situation, you will do whatever you can do to escape it.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you feel like you aren’t in control of your destiny, you will give up and accept whatever situation you are in.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Embodied Cognition
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Your opinions of people and events are based on objective evaluation.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You translate your physical world into words, and then believe those words.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anchoring Effect
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You rationally analyze all factors before making a choice or determining value.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Your first perception lingers in your mind, affecting later perceptions and decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attention
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You see everything going on before your eyes, taking in all the information like a camera.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You are aware only of a small amount of the total information your eyes take in, and even less is processed by your conscious mind and remembered.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Self-Handicapping
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In all you do, you strive for success.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You often create conditions for failure ahead of time to protect your ego.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Self-Fulfilling Prophecies
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Predictions about your future are subject to forces beyond your control.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Just believing a future event will happen can cause it to happen if the event depends on human behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Moment
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You are one person, and your happiness is based on being content with your life.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You are multiple selves, and happiness is based on satisfying all of them.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consistency Bias
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You know how your opinions have changed over time.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Unless you consciously keep tabs on your progress, you assume the way you feel now is the way you have always felt.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Representativeness Heuristic
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Knowing a person’s history makes it easier to determine what sort of person they are.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You jump to conclusions based on how representative a person seems to be of a preconceived character type.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expectation
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wine is a complicated elixir, full of subtle flavors only an expert can truly distinguish, and experienced tasters are impervious to deception.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wine experts and consumers can be fooled by altering their expectations.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Illusion of Control
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You know how much control you have over your surroundings.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You often believe you have control over outcomes that are either random or are too complex to predict.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Fundamental Attribution Error
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Other people’s behavior is the reflection of their personality.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Other people’s behavior is more the result of the situation than their disposition.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-notes" /><summary type="html">The Book This book, written by David McRaney, is available here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Modern Problems and Ancient Solutions</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2018/11/23/modern-problems-and-ancient-solutions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modern Problems and Ancient Solutions" /><published>2018-11-23T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-11-23T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2018/11/23/modern-problems-and-ancient-solutions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2018/11/23/modern-problems-and-ancient-solutions.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-book&quot;&gt;The Book&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book, written by Swami Harshananda, is available
&lt;a href=&quot;https://istore.chennaimath.org/product/modern-problems-and-ancient-solutions/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this book Swami Harshananda starts by showing the problems faced by the
modern society. Later, he suggests an ‘instant pill’ as a solution to these
problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Satyam Vada. Dharmam Chara.&lt;/em&gt; (Speak truth always and act righteously).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keeping our bodies fit through proper food and exercise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acquiring enough professional competence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do nothing in excess&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving our intellect by studying philosophy, logic or social sciences&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing a sense of appreciating art-forms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Praying and meditating everyday&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Practising the three principles of life
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;ahimsa and daya&lt;/em&gt; (non-violence and compassion)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;asteya and aparigraha&lt;/em&gt; (non-greediness and contentment)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;brahmacharya&lt;/em&gt; (controlling of base passions)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-notes" /><summary type="html">The Book This book, written by Swami Harshananda, is available here.</summary></entry></feed>