<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-23T07:14:05+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Quagmire</title><subtitle>Stuff I find cool/useful</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Self-Discipline</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/04/23/self-discipline.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self-Discipline" /><published>2021-04-23T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-04-23T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/04/23/self-discipline</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/04/23/self-discipline.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short book by Curtis Leone talks about the reasons most of lack the
self-discipline needed to achieve our goals and steps to be taken in order to
improve it. This book can be found
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Self-Discipline-Mindset-Lacking-Unleash/dp/1544660472&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;self-discipline is the control you have over your emotions, behaviours, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;willpower is your ability to decide and start on the course towards your goal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;willpower helps you get started, whereas self-discipline keeps you on the course.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some points about self-discipline:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it is not something your born with, but have developed through practice
and hardwork.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;bad experiences in our past prohibit us from thinking positively and shape
negative behaviours in us&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;fear of failing often keeps us from taking initiatives, which keeps us from
developing self-discipline&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;having low self-esteem and self-confidence will make you unaware of your
strengths in getting things done&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;lack of purpose or a goal in life can also make you lose self-discipline&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make sure you:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;have a good reason for developing self-discipline (helps you keep going)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;know what you want and why you want it&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;don’t wait for the “right time” to get started on something
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;in order to break an old habit and make a new one, we need to actively start
using our decision making ability&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;stop making excuses to delaying tasks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;when you are making excuses, try to first find the real reason behind them&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prepare an action plan detailing the steps needed to achieve your goal
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;anticipate potential roadblocks and strategies to overcome them&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;keep tracking your progress and make amendments to the plan if necessary&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;if mistakes are made don’t blame yourself. Instead, look at how to learn
from your mistakes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work on overcoming your temptations
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;detach from the attractions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;envision yourself resisting the temptations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;compare immediate gratification against long-term benefits of not giving into them&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;motivate and nurture yourself
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;reward yourself with something else when you don’t give in to the temptations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;take care of your health&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;reduce stress in your life&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="self-help" /><category term="book-notes" /><summary type="html">Introduction A short book by Curtis Leone talks about the reasons most of lack the self-discipline needed to achieve our goals and steps to be taken in order to improve it. This book can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Seven habits of highly effective people</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/04/11/seven-habits-of-highly-effective-people.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Seven habits of highly effective people" /><published>2021-04-11T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-04-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/04/11/seven-habits-of-highly-effective-people</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/04/11/seven-habits-of-highly-effective-people.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This very popular book by Stephen Covery teaches the seven habits that we all
must inculcate to lead an effective and fruitful life. This book can be found
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.franklincovey.com/the-7-habits/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;TLDR&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Habit1 - Be proactive. Focus on things you can control&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Habit2 - Begin with the end in mind. Define a clear goal that is aligned with
your life’s mission.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Habit3 - Put first things first. Prioritize the tasks apriori, instead of
reacting to urgent things.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Habit4 - Think win-win. Life is not a zero-sum game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Habit5 - Seek first to understand, then to be understood. Which helps in
influencing others by deeply understanding their PoV and needs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Habit6 - Synergize. Whole is greater than the sum of its parts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Habit7 - Sharpen the saw. Spend time in renewing your skills, acquiring new
ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;foreword&quot;&gt;foreword&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;interdependence is a higher value than independence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we achieve success only when we are in harmony with the principles that govern
the success itself&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some of our most difficult challenges are:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;fear and insecurity (of the future) - and we become more risk-averse. But to
succeed we need to be interdependent in this complex world&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“I want it all now” mentality - we need to balance between short term and
long term growth&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;blame and vicitimism - we should own our mistakes and work towards
rectifying them&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;hopelessness - caused by believing that we are the victims&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;lack of balance in life - we need to have priorities and defend them fiercely&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;what’s in it for me? - we seem to treat everything in life as a competition.
We should work selflessly with mutual respect for mutual benefit&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;hunger to be understood - we want to be understood, but we aren’t ready to
deeply listen to others&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;inability to cope with conflicts and differences&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;paradigms-and-principles&quot;&gt;paradigms and principles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our perceptions govern the way we see, which in turn govern the way we behave&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pre-WWI, success was defined by character ethic: integrity, humility, fidelity,
temperance, courage, industry, patience, simplicity, modesty, etc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;post-WWI, success was defined by personality ethic: public image, behaviour,
attitude, skills, techniques. Those which lubricate the process of human interaction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;elements of personality ethic are essential for success. But for long term,
continued success character ethic is critical&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what you are speaks louder than what you do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;paradigm is the way we perceive the world. It is like having a map. If our map
itself is wrong, no matter of we improve our behavior or attitude, we’ll still
end up at a wrong place&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we have many mental maps or paradigms in us. They are of 2 main categories:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the way things are (reality)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the way things we want things to be (values).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we see things in this world not as they are, but as we are!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;conditioning can very powerfully affect our perceptions and paradigms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when others disagree with our views,  we immediately think that something’s
wrong with them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the way we think and act are based on the assumption that &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;reality == values&lt;/code&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is futile in the long run, to change our attitudes and behaviours without
understanding the underlying paradigms which gives rise to these.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;where we stand depends on where we sit. If we have a clear and objective pov
about a thing, there could similarly be another clear and objective pov about
the same thing and it might as well be just as right as yours!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;paradigm shifts bring in very powerful changes in us and our society, for
better or for worse.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some paradigm shifts are long and require deliberate processes in place because
paradigms are inseparable from character&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;many of us experience paradigm shifts when we face life-threatening situation
or take on a new role in life/work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;paradigms are the lens through which we see our world&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;principles are not values. If principles were to be the territory, values
would be the map.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it takes time for a baby from rolling over till the time it starts to walk
and run. This is true for all walks of life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;trying to take shortcuts from these natural processes only results in
frustration and disappointment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;admission of ignorance is often the first step in education&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to relate effectively with other humans, we first need to learn to listen
properly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;often times, the way we see the problem is the problem!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the more we look for quick-fixes, the more problems they’ll cause in the
long term&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;personality ethic only teaches us to look for such quick fixes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;significant problems we face cannot be solved at the same level of thinking we
were at when those problems were created - Einstein&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we need to change our paradigms, characters and motives completely in order to
solve these problems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;this is the inside-out approach. We should start within ourselves first.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are what we repeatedly do. This excellence is not an act but a habit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our character is a composite of our habits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;habits are like the pull of gravity. They are very difficult to break&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;habit is formed through the intersection of what to do (knowledge), how to do
(skill) and the want to do (desire)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;happiness is the ability to sacrifice what we want now for what we want
eventually&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;maturity - it is the growth of an individual from dependent to independent to
interdependent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;interdependence is about us cooperating among each other for something greater
than ourselves. This is the mark of a true leader or a team player&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;effectiveness lies in maintaining the “P/PC balance”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;remembering Aesop’s golden goose story, we need to make sure that we give
adequate attention to both the production and the production capacity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in our life
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;production = the results&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;production capacity = the asset producing the results or the ability&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;three kinds of assets are
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;physical - P is the purpose of this asset (eg: car for transport) and PC is
its timely maintenance.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;financial - our most important asset here is our own capacity to earn (P).
If we don’t invest in ourselves (PC), we’ll end up with limited options.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;human - P/PC balance here is even more critical, as people control both
physical and financial assets!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in every interaction or relation, figure out your goose and its eggs. Then
earnestly work towards its P/PC balance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PC principle is to treat your employees exactly the same way as you want them
to treat your customers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no one can persuade another to change. It can only happen from within&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;self-growth is the greatest investment, but it’ll be evolutionary, whereas
it’s results will be revolutionary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;private-victory&quot;&gt;private victory&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;habit-1---be-proactive&quot;&gt;habit 1 - be proactive&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;self-awareness is unique to us and we can use this very same thing to make and
break our habits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we can also use this to examine our paradigms and check whether they are based
on reality/principles or are they based on conditioning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there are 3 social maps that are used to determine the nature of man
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;genetic determinism&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;psychic determinism&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;environmental determinism&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;however, can these factors be the sole reason to define a man’s nature?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Victor Frankl’s story goes along to show that between stimulus and response,
is our freedom (no matter the circumstances!) to choose the latter&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;being proactive means knowing that we are responsible for our own lives&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our behavior is a function of our decisions, not our conditions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we are by nature proactive. So if we become reactive in the process, it’s
because we have let external circumstances to control us!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;highly proactive people don’t blame outside things for their behavior. They
know that it is due to their own conscious choice, which is based on values
not feelings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they have the ability to subordinate an impulse to a value&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what matters the most is how we respond to what happens to us in life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;most of the times, we know about what needs to be done. But only a few of us
are willing to take the initiative to get it done&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;use your R and I (resourcefulness and initiative)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to be effective, we need to act and not be acted upon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this requires us to be proactive about what’s our response to the situation
should be&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;examining our own language can tell us a lot about our mental maps and our
paradigms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reactive people always absolve themselves from responsibility&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;eg: reactive people treat “love” as a feeling, something beyond their control.
Proactive people see it as a verb. Something one does, the sacrifices one
makes for their loved ones&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;circle of concern (CoC) - list of things that we get concerned about&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;circle of influence (CoI) - things in CoC over which we have our influence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;proactive people focus on CoI, thereby increasing their CoI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;however, reactive people focus on CoC, thereby further shrinking their CoI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by working on ourselves instead of the conditions, we will be able to
influence the conditions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;having CoI to be larger than CoC is also an indication of myopic and reactive
nature of that person too!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the problems we face fall into 3 categories:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;direct control - involve our own behavior. Can be solved by working on our
habits&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;indirect control - involve other people’s behavior. Can be solved by working
our influence&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;no control - we cannot do anything about them. Eg: our past. Solved by just
accepting them by their face value&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;oh god… give us the courage to change the things which we can change,
maturity to accept the things which we can’t and the wisdom know the difference&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;first step in solving all these problems lies in our CoI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by choosing how to respond to our circumstances, we can greatly influence
the outcome&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CoC is filled with the “have”s&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CoI is filled with the “be”s&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;anytime we think that the problem is “out there”, that thought is itself the
problem!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we are free to choose our actions, but cannot choose the consequences of
those.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if we chose a wrong response and if we now regret about it, then that’s a
mistake.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thus, both consequences and mistakes are part of our CoC.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to be proactive, it is important to admit our mistakes instantly, learn from
them and correct ourselves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;proactivity is mainly governed by our ability to make and keep commitments and
promises.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this also gives us courage to be responsible for our own lives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;habit-2---begin-with-the-end-in-mind&quot;&gt;habit 2 - begin with the end in mind&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what lies behind and before us is nothing compared to what lies within us&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is easy to work harder and climb the success ladder, only to see that it is
finally leaning against the wrong wall.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is possible to be very busy without being effective&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by keeping end in mind, we have a clear destination, a core set of values in
mind, that guide us everyday along a clear path&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all of us create things twice: first in our minds and then physically&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if we don’t consciously design this thing in our mind first, then we’ll end up
having other people or circumstances to dictate it for us&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;if habit 1 says “you are the creator”, then habit 2 is the first creation&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;management is doing things right and leadership is doing the right thing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;more often parenting and also our personal lives, we are into day-to-day
managing rather than thinking about where we are headed&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;having a personal mission statement is very helpful (as it is determined by
keeping end in mind)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;at the center of your CoI is your personal mission statement. It is then
expanded by working on these 4 interdependent factors:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;security - your sense of worth&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;guidance - your source of direction in life&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;wisdom - your perspective on life&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;power - your capacity to act&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by starting to work on these factors, you gradually expand your CoI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;many of us center our lives on wrong things. Eg. Self, spouse, family, work,
money, possession, church, etc. Maybe even combination of these things and
over time. Solely depending on these factors to derive our sense of self-worth
can hurt our security, guidance, wisdom and power.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;our sense of security, guidance, wisdom and power are drawn from these centers
which are not derived intrinsically, but from external sources&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hence, it always is superior to live life centered around principles that don’t
change under circumstances&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this should be the center of all the other centers mentioned above.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;with being principle centered, you don’t act based on people or circumstances.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;most of us tend to dominantly use only one half of our brain. We need to
cultivate the habit of assessing the situation and accordingly using the right
tool to solve it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;specifically, our world is becoming increasingly reliant on left-brain usage.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to change our behavior, use the affirmation process. Vividly imagine the scenario
and then script out your behavior during that scenario. Repeat this exercise for
multiple days.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;define your roles and goals in each of your role. They’ll help provide a clear
structure and direction to your personal mission statement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if there’s no involvement, then there’s no commitment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;habit-3---put-first-things-first&quot;&gt;habit 3 - put first things first&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;things which matter the most must never be at the mercy of things which matter
the least&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;manage from the left, lead from the right&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;organize and execute around priorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there are 4 kinds of activities on which we spend our time:
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;important-and-urgent&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;important-but-not-urgent&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;not-important-but-urgent&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;not-important-and-not-urgent&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To be an effective self-manager, your discipline should be a function of your
independent will&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Effective people stay in the quadrant 2. They also completely avoid not-important
tasks (Q3 and Q4)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;effective people are not problem-minded but are opportunity-minded&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by staying in Q2, we think ahead and prevent problems from being crises (thereby
moving to Q1)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to be able to spend more time on quadrant-II we should learn to say “no” to other
things, even the apparently urgent ones&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by centering on the wrong things, we keep getting pulled into Q1 and Q3 all
the times&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a Q2 oriented tool should focus on
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;being coherent - with P/PC balance, personal mission statement&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;maintain balance - between all your roles&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;focus on Q2 - thus instead of scheduling daily, it should help plan on a weekly basis&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;add a people dimension - as sometimes we have to surrender our schedules to people&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;flexible - tool is your servent, not the other way around&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;portable - easy to carry around&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;organizing for Q2 involves:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;identifying roles&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;defining goals for each role as per priority&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;scheduling tasks weekly&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;adapting the tasks daily&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be effective with people and efficient with things&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;so, at times we have to submit our schedules for a higher purpose. But since we
will be principle driven, we should be able to do so with ease.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;key to effective management is delegation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;trust is the highest form of human motivation, but it takes time and patience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;public-victory&quot;&gt;public victory&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;paradigms-of-interdependence&quot;&gt;paradigms of interdependence&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can’t be successful with others if you aren’t successful with yourself&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building relationships is a time-consuming process
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;understand the individual&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;attending to the little things&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;keeping commitments&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;clarifying expectations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;showing personal integrity&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;apologize sincerely when you make a withdrawal from the emotional bank account&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when you defend those who are absent, you earn the trust of those who are present&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is more noble to give yourself completely to one individual than to labor for
the salvation of the masses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in interdependent situations, every P problem is a PC opportunity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;habit-4--&quot;&gt;habit 4 -&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can’t get the fruits of cooperation from a paradigm of competition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can’t change the fruit without changing the root&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;different approaches in human interaction:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;win/win - seeks mutual benefit of all involved parties. Very essential when
the environment is highly interdependent&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;win/lose - most of us are primed with this competitive mentality. This
prohibits cooperation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;lose/win - seekers of acceptance. But it makes them cynical and depressive&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;lose/lose - typically happens when 2 win/lose people confront each other&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;win - one who always wants to win. doesn’t necessarily care about whether
other person loses or wins&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;win/win or no deal - if both parties can’t come to a mutual agreement it is
better to walk away.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;which approach to use always depends on the situation. However lose/lose is
just not viable. If this situation is about interdependence then win/win is the
best, but with the option of walking away if no conclusion can be reached&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;many times we think of win/lose or lose/win as win/win. It is very important
to accurately identify them as these can cause problems later&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;five dimensions of win/win
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;character - integrity (with our core values), maturity (balance between
courage and consideration) and abundance mentality (there’s enough out there
for everybody)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;relationships
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;through strong character we develop healthy relationships&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;this matters a lot when dealing with a win/lose person&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;agreements
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;definition and direction to win/win results&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;win/win agreement has 5 elements:
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;desired results (not methods)&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;guidelines or frameworks within which the above results are to be produced&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;resources to help accomplish the results&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;accountability to track performance and evaluate success&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;consequences of evaluation (good/bad)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;it can only come out through successful character and relationships&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;systems - reward systems must be aligned with the goals and values&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;processes - win/win results are achieved through processes that are defined
in habits 5 and 6&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;habit-5---seek-first-to-understand-then-to-be-understood&quot;&gt;habit 5 - seek first to understand, then to be understood&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all of us learn how to read, write and speak. However, very few of us listen!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we listen with an intent to reply!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;levels of listening
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ignoring&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;pretending&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;selective&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;attentive&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;empathic (seeking first to understand, without any judgement)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sympathy means to agree with the person, whereas empathy is to fully
understand them without necessarily having to agree with them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what is satisfied will not motivate us&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;next to physical survival is psychological: to be understood, to be affirmed
and validated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;diagnose first before you prescribe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;because if you don’t have confidence in the diagnosis, you won’t have
confidence in the prescription&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if we listen always from our PoV, we either only:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;probe - ask questions from our frame of reference&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;evaluate - agree or disagree&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;advise - based on our experience&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;interpret - figure our people, their motives etc&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when emotions are involved such a logical left brain approach will only end up
emotional bank withdrawal!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;skills (tip of the iceberg of empathic listening):
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;mimic content - literally&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;rephrase the content - in your own words&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;reflect feeling - focus on what the other person is really feeling&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;reflect and rephrase&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in order to work with the vast differences between our perceptions it helps
when we seek first to understand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;finally, knowing how to be understood is also equally important in arriving at
win/win solutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;seek to understand requires consideration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to be understood requires courage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;right sequence for an effective presentation is: ethos (character), pathos
(feeling) and logos (logic)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when you listen, you learn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;habit-6---synergy&quot;&gt;habit 6 - synergy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;synergy means that the whole is greater than the sum of its parts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it means to respect the differences, build on the mutual strengths while
compensating for each other’s weaknesses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working without synergy is like driving with one foot on brake and the other on gas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;uniformity doesn’t mean unity!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;essence of synergy is in recognising differences and valuing them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in order to achieve interpersonal synergy once must first perfect intrapersonal
synergy (eg: approaching life from both left and right brains)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;because life is not just logical, it is also emotional&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;remember “we all see the world as we are, not as it is”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is possible that we both the see the same situation but have different opinions
on it and yet both be correct&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for any change there’ll be:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;driving forces; which are positive, logical, reasonable, economical&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;restraining forces; which are negative, illogical, emotional, psychological&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;unless we work directly on these restraining forces, just the driving forces
aren’t enough. It’s like pushing against a spring!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can be synergistic with yourself even in a hostile environment. Eg: you don’t
have to take insults personally&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;renewal&quot;&gt;renewal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;habit-7---sharpen-the-saw&quot;&gt;habit 7 - sharpen the saw&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;following are the 4 dimensions of renewal:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;physical - exercise regularly in order to build endurance, flexibility and
strength. It also helps us to be more proactive.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;spiritual - renewal of spirit, people do it very differently: prayer,
meditation, music, etc. “greatest battles of life are fought daily in the
 silent chambers of soul”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;mental - continually educate yourself. We shouldn’t let our minds atrophy.
Write regularly about your thoughts and feelings&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;social/emotional - to help sharpen the saw for habits 4,5,6, in achieving
public victory&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the person who doesn’t read is no better than the one who can’t.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how are we reflecting to others? Is it just what they are or what they can be?
Sometimes, the way we treat or our belief in other people can have significant
influence in their lives&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to keep up with the upward spiral of renewal, we must continually learn,
commit and do; over and over.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="self-help" /><category term="book-notes" /><summary type="html">Introduction This very popular book by Stephen Covery teaches the seven habits that we all must inculcate to lead an effective and fruitful life. This book can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Heterogeneous Graph Transformer</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/02/13/hgt.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Heterogeneous Graph Transformer" /><published>2021-02-13T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-02-13T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/02/13/hgt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/02/13/hgt.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;proposal&quot;&gt;Proposal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Main paper can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.01332&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;uses meta-relations on node and edge types for heterogeneous graphs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;proposes HGT network for working on such graphs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;propose a HGSampling algo tailor-made for this network for the purpose of
minibatch training&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;propose Relative Temporal Encoding (RTE) to work with dynamic graphs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;hetergeneous-mutual-attention&quot;&gt;Hetergeneous mutual attention&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;H^l(t) = Agg_{s \in N(t)}(Att(s, t) Msg(s))&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;where:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t&lt;/script&gt; = target node&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s&lt;/script&gt; = source nodes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;l&lt;/script&gt; = &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;l&lt;/script&gt;-th layer of the network&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;H&lt;/script&gt; = output node embedding of the layer&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Agg&lt;/script&gt; = heterogeneous aggregation function. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Agg(.) = \sigma(Mean(.))&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;N&lt;/script&gt; = neighborhood of the target node&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Att&lt;/script&gt; = heterogeneous edgewise attention weights&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Msg&lt;/script&gt; = heterogeneous message passing from the source nodes. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Msg(s) = W H^{l-1}(s)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;L&lt;/script&gt; = number of layers in the network&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hetergeneous Attention
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Att(s, t) = softmax_{s \in N(t)}(concat_{i \in [1,h]}(AttHead^i(s, e, t))&lt;/script&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h&lt;/script&gt; = number of attention heads&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;AttHead^i(s, e, t) = K^i(s) W^{ATT}_{\phi(e)} Q^i(t)^T \frac{\mu_{\tau(s),\phi(e),\tau(t)}}{\sqrt{d}}&lt;/script&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\phi&lt;/script&gt; = edge types&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tau&lt;/script&gt; = node types&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mu&lt;/script&gt; = significance weights based on the meta relation triplet&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d&lt;/script&gt; = dimensionality of the final attention output&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;K^i(s) = KLinear^i_{\tau(s)}(H^{l-1}(s))&lt;/script&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Q^i(t) = QLinear^i{\tau(t)}(H^{l-1}(t))&lt;/script&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W^{ATT}_{\phi(e)}&lt;/script&gt; = edge-based attention weights&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heterogeneous message passing
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Msg(s, e, t) = concat_{i \in [1,h]}(MsgHead^i(s, e, t))&lt;/script&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;MsgHead^i(s, e, t) = MLinear^i_{\tau(s)}(H^{l-1}(s)) W^{MSG}_{\phi(e)}&lt;/script&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;W^{MSG}_{\phi(e)}&lt;/script&gt; = edge-based message weights&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;target specific aggregation
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;H^{~(l)}(t) = \Sigma_{s \in N(t)}(Att(s, e, t) . Msg(s, e, t))&lt;/script&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;H^l(t) = ALinear_{\tau(t)}(\sigma(H^{~(l)}(t))) + H^{l-1}(t)&lt;/script&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rte&quot;&gt;RTE&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to help work with dynamic graphs with timestamps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;based on Transformer’s positional encoding technique&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\Delta(t, s) = T(t) - T(s)&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T&lt;/script&gt; = timestamp associated with the nodes/edges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;B(\Delta(t, s), 2i) = sin(\frac{\Delta(t, s)}{10000^{\frac{2i}{d}}})&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;B(\Delta(t, s), 2i+1) = cos(\frac{\Delta(t, s)}{10000^{\frac{2i+1}{d}}})&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;RTE(\Delta(t, s)) = TLinear(Base(\Delta(t, s)))&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finally, the input node-embeddings at &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;l&lt;/script&gt;-th layer will be:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;H^{~(l)}(s) = H^{l-1}(s) + RTE(\Delta(t, s)&lt;/script&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hgsampling&quot;&gt;HGSampling&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;sampling method needs to be aware of different node and edge types so as not
to create imbalances in sampling and reduce variance in sampling&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AddInBudget(B, t, A, NS)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for each source node type &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tau&lt;/script&gt; and edge type &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\phi&lt;/script&gt;:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;normalized node-degree &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D_t = \frac{1}{len(A_{\tau(s), \phi(e), \tau(t)}(t))}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;for source node &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s&lt;/script&gt; in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A_{\tau(s), \phi(e), \tau(t)}(t)&lt;/script&gt;:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;if &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s&lt;/script&gt; is not sampled:
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;if &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s&lt;/script&gt; has no timestamp then &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s.time = t.time&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;update &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;B(\tau)(s) += D_t&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t \in NS&lt;/script&gt;:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;AddInBudget(B, t, A, NS)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;l \in [1, L]&lt;/script&gt;:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;for source node type &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tau \in B&lt;/script&gt;:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;for source node &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s \in B(\tau)&lt;/script&gt;:
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;compute probability &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p^{l-1}(\tau)(s) = \frac{B(\tau)(s)^2}{L2Norm(B(\tau))^2}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;sample &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;n&lt;/script&gt; nodes &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t^n_i&lt;/script&gt; from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;B(\tau)&lt;/script&gt; using &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p^{l-1}(\tau)&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t \in t^n_i&lt;/script&gt;:
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;OS(\tau).add(t)&lt;/script&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;AddInBudget(B, t, A, NS)&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;B(\tau).pop(t)&lt;/script&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;construct the adjacency matrix for the subsampled graph&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt; = adjacency matrix&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;B&lt;/script&gt; = budget info used for computing probability of sampling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;NS&lt;/script&gt; = sampled node set&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;OS&lt;/script&gt; = output sampled node set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="tech-notes" /><category term="paper-notes" /><category term="graph" /><category term="gnn" /><summary type="html">Proposal Main paper can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">David and Goliath</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/01/22/david-and-goliath.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="David and Goliath" /><published>2021-01-22T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-01-22T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/01/22/david-and-goliath</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/01/22/david-and-goliath.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this book Malcolm Gladwell, through series of real life incidents, shows that
more is not always better and less is not always bad; as paradoxical as it
sounds! Through various examples from history, he demonstrates the importance of
inverted U-curve while making decisions. He shows that depending on the vantage
point, what we usually perceive as advantages can turn out to be disdvantages
and vice-versa. This book can be found
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/David-Goliath-Underdogs-Misfits-Battling/dp/0316204374&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;introduction-1&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sometimes, the strength of these giants can become the source of their weakness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;act of facing overwhelming odds can change people, but we often misinterpret it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;key points to note in this epic fight:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;David was a slinger (artillery), whereas Goliath was an infantry. Slingers
always beat infantry.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Goliath was expecting another infantry for a hand-to-hand battle and thus
was heavily armored, making him slow in his movements.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;David had no intention of doing so with no armor and so could maneuver
quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;power comes not only in size but also with speed and surprise&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Goliath had an assistant to hold his shield, that was mostly because to
guide him as he couldn’t see. (He says, “sticks” when David was carrying
only one)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Israeli army saw Goliath and jumped to conclusions about what he could do.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-advantages-of-disadvantages-and-disadvantages-of-advantages&quot;&gt;The advantages of disadvantages (and disadvantages of advantages)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there are certainly advantages of having material resources. But there are
also equal advantages of not having those!- we have a very rigid definition of
what an advantage is and thus we find a David-Goliath event to be a surprise
always&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the underdog and the misfits have little invested in the conventions. Thus
they end up trying things that are unheard of&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;most parents would love to enroll their children to schools with less crowd
because they are convinced that lesser students means more individual
attention from the teachers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;however, many studies have found no correlation/causation between these two
things!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;just like children of poor struggle, the kids of the wealthy also struggle as
they are spoiled by the comfort and have lost their ambition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;so both the ends of the spectrum suffer and probably it’s somewhat better at
the middle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thus the curve of easyness of parenting as a function of the parents’ wealth
is an inverted U-curve!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;inverted U-curves are notorious in showing to us that doing/having more not
necessarily means more “output”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all positive traits and experiences have an inherent cost and at high levels
these costs will outweigh their benefits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;everyone of us want to compete fiercely in order to get into the finest
institutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have we ever considered that is it good for us to be small fish in a big pond
or a big fish in a small pond of our choosing!?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in the big pond, there’s always a chance of experiencing “relative deprivation”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we form our impressions by comparing to folks ‘in the same boat’, rather than
comparing globally&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and our impressions are the starting point for motivation and confidence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the smarter your peers, the dumber you feel!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;theory-of-desirable-difficulty&quot;&gt;theory of desirable difficulty&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we all want to avoid disadvantages as they can set us back. However there are
a few “desirable difficulties” which bring with them their own advantages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;eg: many of the successful entrepreneurs are dyslexic!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if you have to overcome a hurdle, people do it better when we increase the
difficulty a bit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;however, it should be duly noted that not all difficulties are desirable!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;most of us excel in the things that we are good at. Because we are good at
something, we like to do it more often and the more we do the better we get.
This is “capitalisation learning”. This is easy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;desirable difficulties on the other hand force you to compensate for what’s
lacking (aka “compensation learning”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thus what is learnt out of necessity is much stronger than what comes as easy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the prediction of Londoners to the WWII German bombings were completely wrong.
People went with their daily business as if nothing had happened.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;basically there are 3 groups of people created by these bombings:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;casualties - they are gone and can never cause panic&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;near misses - the wounded or traumatized&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;remote misses - these will start to feel a strange sense of invulnerability!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and we all know self-confidence is the very father and mother of courage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and in a big city like London, there were far more remote misses than near
misses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;too often we jump to the conclusion that there can only be one response to
traumatic experience. But from the above example it’s clear that there can be
two!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gifted children and prodigies tend to come in highly supportive families
whereas geniuses grow up in adverse conditions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;courage is not acquired but earned through triumph against tough times&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;affective forecasting - predicting how we feel about a future event. We are
pretty bad at it!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;moral of the Brer rabbit stories was that even the weakest can triumph in a
lopsided event if they were willing to use their wits- in other words, one
gets an unexpected freedom from having nothing to lose&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a trickster is not a trickster by nature, but by necessity. Necessity coming
out of playing a very unfair game&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-limits-of-power&quot;&gt;the limits of power&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it’s been said that the revolutions are not caused by revolutionaries but by
the stupidity and brutality of the governments. And what happened in Northern
Ireland was just this&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we often think authority to be the answer to disobedience. But at times,
disobedience can itself be due to authority!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when the people in authority want the rest to behave, it first depends on how
they behave&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;principle of legitimacy:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;people should have a feeling that their voices are being heard&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;rules should be the same for all&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;rules should apply to everybody the same way&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;those who give orders are very vulnerable of the opinions of those who are
receiving their orders. Hence, legitimacy is highly needed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="self-help" /><category term="book-notes" /><summary type="html">Introduction In this book Malcolm Gladwell, through series of real life incidents, shows that more is not always better and less is not always bad; as paradoxical as it sounds! Through various examples from history, he demonstrates the importance of inverted U-curve while making decisions. He shows that depending on the vantage point, what we usually perceive as advantages can turn out to be disdvantages and vice-versa. This book can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Leadership: Practical Leadership Skills</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/01/18/practical-leadership-skills.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Leadership: Practical Leadership Skills" /><published>2021-01-18T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-01-18T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/01/18/practical-leadership-skills</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/01/18/practical-leadership-skills.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This online video course by Chris Croft talks about various management and
leadership styles and skills to help us become a better leader. This course can
be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.udemy.com/course/practical-leadership/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Given below
are the raw notes I took while attending this course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leaders are about vision and managers are about execution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leader is like a captain of a ship
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;we dont want him to care about customer care&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;we dont want him to serve food, prepare our bed&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;we want him to steer the ship and NOT crash!&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a good boss is hands-off and knows how to delegate&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leadership is all about people - system - vision
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;has got all the right people for the job&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a system is in place and it works&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;vision about where the company is going&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if the system crashes, it is the leadership’s fault, even in their absence!
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;if everything runs fine for a few weeks even in the absence of the manager
means that he’s a good boss&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;everything is the management’s fault!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;connecting with the team, aka communication (a very important thing!)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;management by wandering about - check if your managers are running a tight
ship by just “walking” around the workplace&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;back to the floor - a few days per year, go back and work with the lowest
levels of the org. Also helps you with getting back in touch with the work,
thereby helping you make better decisions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;information cascade - along the management chain and then use MBWA to check
if this is really working&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;team meetings - all your reportees, per week (can keep it snappy)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;addressing the troops - address your full org about profits, revenues and
investments and plans for the next year&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;good leaders are because of what they DO not what they ARE
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;get the tasks done&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;keep the team happy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;keep the individuals happy&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maslow’s hierarchy of needs (we can’t skip the stages and they go in that order)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;physiological needs - survival&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;saftey/security - as a manager we need to provide this! Communicate clearly
about the status of the reportees, be consistent&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;belongingness - social&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;esteem/status - be noticed&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;self-fulfillment - this is an internal motivator&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;as a leader, we need to bring everyone to the final stage of self-actualization&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;management potato - thanking people
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it is essential for security, status and self-actualization&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;most of us are doing ok 80% of the times, excellent 10% and not so good 10%&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;but the management typically focuses only on the last 10%!&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;that criticism can demotivate employees and they stop doing work&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;so focus on the middle 10% and praise them for that&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;but for the last 10%, ask them “what will you do differently to improve?”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leader needs to adopt to the different types of personalities
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;{introvert, extrovert} x {logical, emotional}&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introvert+logical =&amp;gt; analytical
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;give them freedom&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;might prefer self-actualization more&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introvert+emotional =&amp;gt; amiable
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;need to be felt safe and heard&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;extrovert+logical =&amp;gt; controller
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;motivated by challenges&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;might be hard to manage&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;extrovert+emotional =&amp;gt; enthusiast
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;very social and status oriented&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;might be disorganized&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how will they be as leaders?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introvert+logical =&amp;gt; analytical
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;communicates clearly (mostly 1:1)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;like to have a plan and organized, might not be risk takers&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introvert+emotional =&amp;gt; amiable
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;good at judging and putting right set of people to work together&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;can be good senior managers&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;extrovert+logical =&amp;gt; controller
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;very dynamic&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;might not be sympathetic&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;extrovert+emotional =&amp;gt; enthusiast
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;visionary and inspirational leader&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;need to remember the details&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;money is not a motivator
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it is actually a PUSH motivator. IOW, it will push you to do things, but not
necessarily want you to do things (as opposed to a PULL motivator, which
makes us want to do things)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;pay raise does give some temporary motivation. But it is really the praise
that’s a bigger motivator than the money associated with it&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;motivational tips
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;give everyone ownership of something&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;involve people in decision making as much as possible&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;give out challenges&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;let them set their own objectives&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;do regular appraisals&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;make them feel secure&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;praise freely&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;thank as much as possible&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;coach and support (instead of criticize)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;get to know your people and motivate&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;offer learning&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;show progress&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;co-develop (vision of where their learning is going to go)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;help them reach their potentials&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;give people who need, the novelty in work&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;provide a sociable work env&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;build team spirit&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;make money adequate&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;set an example to your org&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tannenbaum and schmidt management continuum
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it’s all about deciding how much control you want to have&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;continuum is: tells -&amp;gt; sells -&amp;gt; shares -&amp;gt; consults -&amp;gt; delegates&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;this is in increasing order of freedom for your team, or decreasing order
of your control&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;final stage is empowerment where we are not monitoring but are available for
support/consultation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;delegating (or empowering)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;provides a sense of ownership and motivation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;frees your time&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;helps others learn&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;increases bus factor and thereby reduces risk&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;acts as a training experience&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;abdicating is basically delegating but not available for support and coaching!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;people don’t delegate because of the fear
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;that it might go wrong - but it is unfounded since you’ll be monitoring and
supporting all the way!&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;that they might be better than me - which is fine because that’ll make you
look good in front of your boss!&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;that they might be overloaded - but by giving them more work, they might
become efficient! Remember that they’ll always look busy in front of you!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if your team can function for a few weeks to months without you, then you have
delegated (or even empowered) them sufficiently!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;don’t take the monkey
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;if they come with a problem, don’t say “leave it with me”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ask questions (or guide) to let them come with a plan and then follow-up&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;remember, you are the boss and they work for you!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“situational” leadership
    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;                   competency
              low                    high
motivation
     high    enthusiatic           experienced

     low     lacking confidence    bored
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;freedom ladder (types of workers)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;wait until told&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ask what’s next&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;suggest next&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;just do it and report afterwards&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;free to act (occasional reporting only)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tannenbaum and schmidt is for planning and freedom ladder for doing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;let your team help you in becoming a better boss!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="leadership" /><category term="udemy-notes" /><summary type="html">Introduction This online video course by Chris Croft talks about various management and leadership styles and skills to help us become a better leader. This course can be found here. Given below are the raw notes I took while attending this course.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Introduction To Emotional Intelligence</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/01/11/an-introduction-to-emotional-intelligence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Introduction To Emotional Intelligence" /><published>2021-01-11T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-01-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/01/11/an-introduction-to-emotional-intelligence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/01/11/an-introduction-to-emotional-intelligence.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This online video course by Robin Hills introduces students to the concept of
Emotional Intelligence and why and how is it essential at work place. This
course can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.udemy.com/course/introduction-to-emotional-intelligence/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
Given below are the raw notes I took while attending this course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emotional Intelligence (EI) is a way to combine thinking and feelings in order
to make better/creative decisions and to build authentic relationships. It
helps us with dealing with or controlling emotions too.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an example EI response would be: praise in public, criticize in private&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EI is a set of social and emotional skills to
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;understand and express oneself&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;develop and maintain meaningful social relationships&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;cope with challenges in life&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EI and IQ are NOT correlated
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;IQ is a measure of how smart you are&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;EQ (Emotional Quotient) is a measure of how well can you use that smartness&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;EI typically grows with age, whereas IQ growth peaks at ~17yrs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;aka EQ is a measure of EI&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EQ refers to the quantifiable aspects of EI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EI mainly deals with inter and intra personal skills which are important for
personal success&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We should enjoy and use our emotions for our best, not become enslaved by them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;basic emotions (from Paul Ekman)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;happiness&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;fear&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;anger&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;sadness&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;disgust&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;surprise&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;contempt (was added later)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;more complex emotions are formed by mixing of these (just like colors)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;even though these are the basic ones, everyone “feels” about their emotions
differently and it is essential that we learn to pin-point the correct one&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plutchik’s wheel of emotions shows a nice interaction between basic emotions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EI at work is NOT about
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;supressing emotions (but about raising those emotions and working with them)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;being nice (but about doing the right thing and making the right decisions)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how you think about a situation depends on how you feel and vice-versa. Thus
emotional management and engagement are very essential&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;giving feedback
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;feedbacks should help not hurt&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;provide constructive criticism&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ask before they tell&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;be honest and specific&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;receiving feedback
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;listen&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;don’t make excuses or deny&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emotions are always involved when we interact with everyone, even while trying
to access from our memories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;poor ability to read other’s emotions leads to poor social skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emotions are higher-order states that momentarily pass through limbic region
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;conscious experiences are observed in the cortex region&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;unconscious inputs come from limbic region as inputs to cortex region to
become conscious experiences&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;just looking at an image to read another person’s image is not enough and
we’ll require some more context at times
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;people with Mobius syndrome will appear to have a mask-like face&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;so, we cannot judge a person’s emotions just by looking at their face alone&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;some expression of emotions are cultural even&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emotions
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;are a complex set of feelings&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;cause physical/physiological changes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;alter our thought process and behavior&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;are highly subjective&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there are no positive/negative emotions, it is the thought process and
behavior that they trigger which require such labels
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;happiness can’t be expressed in all occassions, eg: funeral&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;happiness can’t help during negotiation or critical thinking&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;anger can be used to right a wrong&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;sadness helps us to be thankful and move on from our loss&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;fear helps us avoid taking unnecessary risks&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;understanding and working with emotions
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;we should recognize what kind of events/circumstances generate what kind of
feelings in us&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;we should develop the capacity to generate the right emotions in order to
focus, reason and communicate&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;identifying how we feel and how others feel&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;what kind of music/art makes me happy/calm/sad etc&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;learn to to detect real vs fake feelings&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Daniel Goleman’s framework for EI
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;motivation - drive to work and succeed (some people are motivated by money)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;self-awareness - understanding of ones strengths and weakness&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;self-regulation - managing one’s own emotions (think before you act)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;empathy - understanding from another’s PoV&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;social skills - working with others&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;                   Awareness             Action

 Inner world    self-awareness ------&amp;gt; self-regulation
                     |                      |
                     |      motivation      |
                     V                      V
 Outer world      empathy -----------&amp;gt; social skills

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EI abilities
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;perceiving emotions - self and others&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;using emotions - to facilitate thinking and problem solving&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;understanding emotions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;managing emotions - to regulate them in self and others&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;six seconds model?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improving EI
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I’m responsible for my own feelings and behavior&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I always have choices on how to respond&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;No one can make me express my emotions unless I choose to do so&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Identify my choices empowers me with a fresh perspective on how to behave&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;recognizing my range of choices is an excellent way to start chaning my
behavior for the better&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;practising EI
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;tune into your emotions (what are you experiencing physically? what are you
feeling?)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;look at the layers of feeling (there could be multiple feelings happening)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Deliberately choose a feeling and intensify it&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;look at optimism with realism&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ask yourself (is this a factual issue or relationship issue?)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;when you are feeling uncertain ask yourself, what will create the most value
for all?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one percent solution
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;identify something that’s a very small but slight improvement and make it an
unconscious habit&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we always try to dwelve on bad things (aka negative bias). This is one of the
main reasons for a lower EI. One way to improve is the “three good things”
method (probably do it at the end of each day)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;think about anything good that has happened to you recently&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;write 3 such good things&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;reflect on why each of those good things have happened&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="leadership" /><category term="udemy-notes" /><summary type="html">Introduction This online video course by Robin Hills introduces students to the concept of Emotional Intelligence and why and how is it essential at work place. This course can be found here. Given below are the raw notes I took while attending this course.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Perfecting Patience</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/01/10/perfecting-patience.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Perfecting Patience" /><published>2021-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/01/10/perfecting-patience</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2021/01/10/perfecting-patience.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this book Dalai Lama discusses the Buddhist practices for perfecting patience
and tolerance, to help overcome anger and hatred. But I found that all the
techniques that he shows here can be practiced by Buddhists and non-Buddhists
alike. This book can be found
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/576117/perfecting-patience-by-the-dalai-lama-translated-by-thupten-jinpa/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-challenge-of-patience&quot;&gt;the challenge of patience&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a moment of anger can destroy the lifetime of merit - Shantideva
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;at first this sounds far fetched and extreme, but if you take into account
the ripple effects of anger, this is certainly true&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;patience cannot be practiced in isolation but in our day to day interaction
with other people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;patience can only be developed once we have some control over our anger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;three characteristics of patience are tolerance:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;based on conscious acceptance of pain and hardship, which helps in
understanding others pain and suffering and be compassionate towards them&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;resulting from reflecting on the nature of reality. The more we are attached
to something the more likely we get angry if we perceive a threat to it. We
need to realise that the actions of others are never done in isolation but
are related to the complex interdependencies in this world.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;towards injuries from others. In reality, you cannot separate the person
from the circumstance that caused him to injure you and only hate him or get
angry at him. Shantideva goes a step further and asks us to consider these
enemies as very precious, since they are the ones who can help us practice
patience!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there’s no evil like hatred. There’s no fortitude like patience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;often the fuel for the anger is some form of discomfort. Finding this
connection is the first step towards controlling anger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;day-one&quot;&gt;day one&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;compassion is a state of mind which is non-violent, non-aggressive and
non-harming.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one aspect of compassion is to respect others’ rights and their views.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hatred is pure evil as it involves having ill-will against others. Whereas
anger can be beneficial some times especially when it is fuelled by compassion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;state of mind is crucial to enjoying our physical health, wealth and
friendship we have.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The only thing that protects us from the destructive effects of anger and
hatred is tolerance and patience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to practice tolerance and patience is to seek the causal factors/conditions
responsible for the origin of anger and hatred, then eliminate those instead
of directly trying to go against these strong emotions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our natural tendency is to dislike suffering and like pleasure. So, any
discomfort/suffering physical or mental will eventually invoke nager and
hatred&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there are only few causes for happiness, but many for suffering. So it is
better for us to increase our tolerance for suffering&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;eg: by being able to tolerate smaller harms, we can prepare ourselves to
tolerate greater ones in future&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hatred, anger and attachment are rooted in ignorance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;day-two&quot;&gt;day two&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;unwholesome actions are the ones done through undisciplined state of mind, and
vice-versa&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;practice of patience and tolerance; love and compassion; complement and
reinforce each other&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;true hero is the one who gains victory over hatred and anger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by meditating on suffering, one can develop empathy towards the others, which
will in turn help us to be more patient and tolerant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We hold grudge on animate objects and never on inanimate objects like
illnesses, when the latter can equally do us harm. Just like the latter, the
former could also have caused the ill-will or hatred that are out of their
control&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;imagine someone close to you losing temper and thereby turning into an “ugly”
being. Then meditate on the effects of such an outrage and realise the
importance of patience and tolerance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;many of the harmful acts are not done with malicious intent but out of pure
ignorance or carelessness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;being angry at disturbed people who harm others is like getting angry at fire
for burning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;being angry at people who harm when under circumstances out of their control
is like blaming the sky for the overcast of clouds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;why should we only hate the person who hits us with a stick and not instead
hate the stick and the circumstances that are also responsible for his act?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we too might have similarly caused pain to others so it is just right that we
too receive the same from others, right?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one’s pain is one’s own creation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;many of us take petty things too seriously and things which have grave impact
on us very lightly!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if someone is insulting us, it doesn’t cause bodily harm. So, why should our
minds be bothered with such acts?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;imagine someone who gets on your nerves says something that irritates you.
Further imagine your natural response to it and then observe the sequence of
events that can unfold due to it. Now, meditate on what would have happened of
you were to practice tolerance instead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;day-three&quot;&gt;day three&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if the person who’s at the recieving end of the harm also gets angry
(ignorantly) with the perpetrator, then both these people are in the same
category&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;just like how we remove all the fire-spreading materials from a burning house
to reduce its spread, we should also do similar thing in order to stop the
spread of hatred. Eg: attachment is the root of hatred&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if one observes carefully, one can see that the reason all conflicts and
fights arise even inside a family is because of strong attachment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if we fall ill, worrying and feeling sorry for ourselves will only add
additional mental burden&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we also cannot blame everything on karma and take a passive attitude towards
life!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;visualize a person suffering badly. Now relate yourself to that person and try
to share their suffering. Now make a resolution that you’ll help all such
sentient beings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when we hear our enemies being praised by others, we shouldn’t be angry or
jealous about it. Instead we should feel happy that this enemy has atleast
made someone else happy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if we expect others to be happy when we are praised, then it’s logical to
reciprocate the same when others are being praised too&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;worrying when our fame/recognition decline is just like children who cry when
their sandcastle topples down&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our ultimate goal is the freedom from suffering. We shouldn’t be distracted
from it due to material gain and honor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there are opportunities for practising generosity but very few for patience.
So we need to be grateful when there are enemies who inflict harm onto us&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in your meditation practice the act of give-and-take. Visualize a very
afflicted individual and give him all your successes whereas take all his
sufferings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;day-four&quot;&gt;day four&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;interaction with sentient beings are very much needed for us to practice
tolerance and patience.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thus one can argue that we should value sentient beings more than the Buddha’s
for their contribution towards our perfection of these virtuous values&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in your meditation, practice thoughtlessness. By default our mind is always
focused on external objects, because of sensory experience. Try to focus
inward. Since there’s no object to focus on, there’s always the chance of
falling asleep! Start by concentrating on your breath and then do meditation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a childish compassion is one where we are compassionate towards the sufferings
of sentient beings but when we come across successful people we become envious
of them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;people with worldly success are plagued by mental/emotional pains whereas the
poor are plagued by physical pains&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this is because we are all under the power and influence of ignorance!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;meditate on the concept of “self”. Self is an aggregation of all our
experiences. There’s always a difference between what we perceive and what the
reality is. The conclusion here is that things are not independent or inherent
as we think of them as. But instead, things are dependent on other factors.
This is what is meant by meditating on emptiness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="self-help" /><category term="book-notes" /><summary type="html">Introduction In this book Dalai Lama discusses the Buddhist practices for perfecting patience and tolerance, to help overcome anger and hatred. But I found that all the techniques that he shows here can be practiced by Buddhists and non-Buddhists alike. This book can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pranic Energization Technique</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/12/29/pet.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pranic Energization Technique" /><published>2020-12-29T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-12-29T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/12/29/pet</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/12/29/pet.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;pranic-energization-technique&quot;&gt;Pranic Energization Technique&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PET (short for “Pranic Energization Technique”) is a book written by
Dr. H. R. Nagendra to show how to use our Prana Shakthi to energize the whole
body and reversing the long-term effects of negative thoughts. This book can be
found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Pranic-Energisation-Technique-PET-Nagendra/dp/8187313102&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PET - short for Pranic Energization Technique.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is the usage of Prana Shakthi to energize our entire body&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is an advanced form of yoga&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prana (life) manifests itself in 5 functional forms in our body:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Prana - which controls upper body and respiration&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Apana - which controls lower body and excretion&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Samana - controls abdominal region and digestion&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Udana - controls upwards movements like belching, vomiting, etc&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Vyana - one which controls touch and is all through the body&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;breath-awareness&quot;&gt;Breath awareness&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;first step towards realizing Prana Shakthi in PET.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;respiration involves 3 phases
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;inspiration aka Puraka&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;hold aka Kumbhaka&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;expiration aka Rechaka&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;start by noticing the breath (to recognize any imbalances or irregularities)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;sit in any comfortable position or Shavasana&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;start watching the breath at the top of the nose&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;recognize any imbalances in breath (eg: breath flow between 2 nostrils), but
don’t control them&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;observe breath becoming continuous, regular and smooth&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;just the act of observing these imbalances helps in reducing them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is believed that left nostril breathing promotes right-lobe of brain and
vice-versa. In yoga:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;left nostril breathing implies Chandra Nadi Prana flow, which is soothing in
nature&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;right nostril breathing implies Surya Nadi Prana flow, which is energizing
in nature&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nadi Shuddhi Pranayama
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a balancing technique for breathing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;take up Sthiti posture&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;adopt Nasika Mudra in right hand&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;inhale through left nostril while closing right nostril with the thumb&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;enjoy the Kevala Kumbhaka&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;open the right nostril and exhale while closing the left nostril via the
ring and index fingers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;enjoy the Kevala Kumbhaka&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;repeat vice-versa on the other side&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;repeat the whole thing for 9 rounds&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kapalabhathi
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;for folks with nasal blockage or observing drowsiness during Nadi Shuddhi
Pranayama can instead practice this&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;cleanses respiratory tract and stimulates brain cells&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;sit in Vajrasana or Padmasana&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;adopt Nasika Mudra in right hand&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;close right nostril with the thumb and breathe in fully through the left
nostril while bulging the abdominal muscles (aka diaphragmatic breathing)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;close the left nostril with little and ring fingers. Open the right nostril&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;exhale with a burst as fast as possible by sucking in abdominal muscles&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;repeat vice-versa on the other side&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;repeat the whole for 60 rounds (at a speed of 60 rounds per minute)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cautions with Kapalabhati practive
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;always do this under empty stomach only&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;don’t contort facial muscles&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;don’t twist nostrils&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;don’t practice if: having high BP, IHD, slip disk, under menstruation, under
pregnancy, spondylosis, etc&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;awareness-and-relaxation&quot;&gt;Awareness and relaxation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improving awareness and sensitivity
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;start with pointed awareness (aka attention)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;carefully trace the movement of breath from nose tip all the way to the lungs
and back. Feel the coolness of air while inspiration and warmness during the
expiration.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;reach a stage of maintaining continuous line of awareness through the path of
breathing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;gradually expand this linear awareness to the inner surfaces of the entire
respiratory tract&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;notice that the breathing stops during end of inhalation and start of
exhalation and vice-versa (aka Kevala Kumbhaka). This induces deep rest and
relaxation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;we can now start feeling our heart beat, pulses in blood vessels. This is the
state of 3D awareness, over the entire body&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bhramari Pranayama
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;while exhaling produce a humming sound, like a bee&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;elongate the duration of humming/breathing without disturbing the flow&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;enjoy the Kevala Kumbhaka and the sound vibrations throughout the body&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;repeat for 9 times&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resonance in Bhramari is the key thing. We should adjust our frequency of the
produced sound so as to feel the resonance throughout the body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sensitization-recognition-and-vyana&quot;&gt;Sensitization, Recognition and Vyana&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mudras - yogic practice to evoke Prana and further sensitize and recognizing
nerve impulses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kriya Mudras - for cleansing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Asana Mudras - practised with breath locks to clam the mind&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pranayama Mudras - associated during pranayama in order to sensitize vyana.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sakthi Calini Mudras - to invoke dormant powers within us&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dhyana Mudras - for meditation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jnana Mudras - for Rsis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recognition of nerve impulses - in PET Adi, Cin, Cinmaya and
Namaskara mudras are used for this purpose
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;sit in a comfortable position and relax the whole body&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;place hands on thighs and adopt Cin mudra&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;observe pulse and heart beat sync&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;open the fingers in Cin mudra and touch again, now recognize the nerve
impulses going from fingers to the brain&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;now adopt Cinmaya mudra&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;press and release the other fingers and feel the impulses (repeat 9 rounds)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;adopt Adi mudra and repeat this press and releas process&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;similarly adopt Namaskara mudra and repeat&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recognition of Vyana: nerve impulses is always unidirectional, to the brain
and they travel at a fixed speed. Vyana has none of these limitations.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;move the palms in and out, bring the palms as close as ~2cms gap between.
Feel that region between the palms getting sensitized. We are experiencing
Vyana in this space. Now rotate both palms clock and anti-clock wise in
order to churn Vyana.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it is this perception of Vyana that will be utilized to energize our systems
and also to improve our immune system.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rotation-and-energization&quot;&gt;Rotation and Energization&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yoga provides a holistic solution to improving our immune system, which is
known to get degraded due to stresses in our daily lives.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;first level is handling at the body level by performing various asanas in
order to improve flexibility and release stress&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;second level is by slowing and balancing of breath through pranayama&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;third level is by handling at emotional and mental levels through yoga nidra
and cyclic meditation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;fourth level is by using the wisdom from Upanishads to correct our notions
about happiness, life, misery and death.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rotating and energization of vyana
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;place the palms on the knees&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;start moving prana from right heel to right calf, right thigh, right buttock
right back and similarly start moving prana from right hand to arm to shoulder
to joints to neck to back of the head, top of head and then coming down from
the front right side of the body all the way back to heel and fingers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;repeat this for the left side&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;now rotate prana simultaneously from both sides&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;growth-and-levels-of-consciousness&quot;&gt;growth and levels of consciousness&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;silence is a state in which the mind, body, prana, emotions and intellect are
completely nullified and are unified with the universe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;practicing silence
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;feel the prana around the body expanding and diffusing into the blue sky&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;experience the bliss associated with it&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;stay for as long as you can&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;if other thoughts come up, focus back on the difussion of prana into the sky&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;harnessing-the-will-and-resolution&quot;&gt;harnessing the will and resolution&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;resolution is a clear and positive thought (eg: I’m ever happy)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we are what we think we are. Such is the power of a thought!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So, a strong positive resolution is very essential&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to be happy, at a state of bliss is everyone’s birthright. All the negative
states are unnatural&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mind is the cause for both bondage and freedom. Our thoughts can transform us&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for maximal effect, such a positive resolve needs to be made when we are in
the blissful state of silence (as described earlier)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;prananusandhana-and-quality-of-life&quot;&gt;prananusandhana and quality of life&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PET is best practiced half hour during morning and evening of each day&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;but for best results, we should spread the experience of prana throughout the
day (aka Anusandhana - act of recollection of prana for revitalizing the whole
being)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;steps are as follows
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;build an awareness of breath throughout the day. Make sure that the breath
is balanced between the 2 nostrils&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;expand the awareness of breath throughout the respiratory tract&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;feel the nerve impulses&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;sensitize further to feel vyana, spread it throughout the body&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;apply rotate and control of vyana flows in order to balance it all across&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;enjoy the diffusion of vyana beyond the body&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;retain this blissful awareness of prana throughout the day&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;continuously introspect and track the growth (if we can measure it, we
certainly can improve it!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="yoga" /><category term="health" /><summary type="html">Pranic Energization Technique PET (short for “Pranic Energization Technique”) is a book written by Dr. H. R. Nagendra to show how to use our Prana Shakthi to energize the whole body and reversing the long-term effects of negative thoughts. This book can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Accelerating 2-opt and 3-opt local search using GPU in TSP</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/12/07/2-opt-3-opt-TSP.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Accelerating 2-opt and 3-opt local search using GPU in TSP" /><published>2020-12-07T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-12-07T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/12/07/2-opt-3-opt-TSP</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/12/07/2-opt-3-opt-TSP.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;proposal&quot;&gt;Proposal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Main paper can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://olab.is.s.u-tokyo.ac.jp/~kamil.rocki/rocki_hpcs2012.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;proposal to parallelize 2-opt and 3-opt swaps on GPUs, over-and-above the
parallelization strategy discussed in &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2020/12/06/parallel-tsp.html&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;
paper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they also further note that due to global memory access latencies, it is
faster to recompute the distances by each thread, instead of pre-computing
them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make each block work on a particular climber and have each thread inside it
work on multiple possible pairs (or triplets).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;then finally do a block-wide reduction to compute the best swap.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this approach helps them to utilize shared memory for storing the city
co-ordinates, as well as for storing the best path&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they also note that pre-computing the distance matrix and accessing them while
doing 2-opt/3-opt swaps leads to random accesses and thereby causing perf
degradation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thus, instead they propose to recompute this value from the input coordinates
by all threads during the process of swap&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the number of cities they can support with this approach is only limited by
the available shared memory capacity on the chip.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the authors however do not talk about the number of climbers used in their
code or even the algorithm used by them (I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; it is IHC as used in the
base paper mentioned above).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="tech-notes" /><category term="paper-notes" /><category term="graph" /><category term="cuda" /><category term="tsp" /><summary type="html">Proposal Main paper can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Parallel GPU version of TSP</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/12/06/parallel-tsp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parallel GPU version of TSP" /><published>2020-12-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-12-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/12/06/parallel-tsp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/12/06/parallel-tsp.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;proposal&quot;&gt;Proposal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Main paper can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://userweb.cs.txstate.edu/~burtscher/papers/pdpta11b.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An optimized GPU version of TSP solver using Iterative Hill Climbing (IHC)
technique&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paper limits itself to 100-cities with 100,000 random restarts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;However, the techniques suggested here can be generalized&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;each thread works on one of the climbers.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;continues to perform the 4851 2-opt moves in each IHC step, until convergence&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;FYI, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;4851 = \frac{(100 - 1) * (100 - 2)}{2}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;after convergence of each climber, a global atomicCAS is performed in order to
update the best solution found so far&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they only compute the incremental TSP cost instead of computing the full path
cost inside IHC step and only compute the global path cost after convergence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all threads continue to fetch their next climber from a global queue until it
is exhausted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;distance matrix is assumed to be pre-computed (for edge weights)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="tech-notes" /><category term="paper-notes" /><category term="graph" /><category term="cuda" /><category term="tsp" /><summary type="html">Proposal Main paper can be found here.</summary></entry></feed>