<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-28T17:01:54+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Quagmire</title><subtitle>Stuff I find cool/useful</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Spartan Discipline</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/05/28/spartan-discipline.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spartan Discipline" /><published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/05/28/spartan-discipline</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/05/28/spartan-discipline.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;spartan-discipline&quot;&gt;Spartan Discipline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Dominic Mann. This book can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Never-Split-Difference-Negotiating-Depended/dp/0062407805&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
Mann gives tips, tricks, suggestions and analogies from Spartan’s lifestyle
to illustrate how to develop self-discipline and be productive in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;full bellies never plough fields&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;choose delayed gratification over the instant one&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;accept minimalism as it allows to inculcate lazer sharp focus, by eliminating
distractions. For someone with no junk in kitchen shelf, eating healthy
becomes easier.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;willpower is like muscle. More you exercise it, the stronger it becomes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;your body can stand almost anything. It’s the mind that’s the bottleneck&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mind over matter!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a healthy mind and body can go a long way in developing self-discipline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;external events are not under your control, but how you react to them is&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;start with the end in mind (what do you want people to say at your funeral)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;conquering yourself is the first step to conquering the world.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;use your emotions as a tool rather than becoming a tool for them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conquer your emotions, not the other way around!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there are 2 kinds of wants
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;wants of the body&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;wants of the mind&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is the wants of the mind that you truly want&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;go all the way in or don’t even start. Don’t give yourself any exceptions, or
else, those exceptions can become the norm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to make big gains avoid tiny losses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is through hardship, challenges and adversity that we grow in life&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;developing discipline in one key area of life also leads to being disciplined
in all areas of life. It’s called developing a “keystone habit”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spartans used to not ask how enemies, but where they are. If you truly want to
do something, find a way to do it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;give your 100% in everything you do.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;do one thing at a time, but with lazer sharp focus. Intensity beats extensity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you just only need enough willpower to get a habit in motion. Once habit takes
over, no willpower is required&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we eventually get adjusted to new circumstances and get back to our normalcy.
So we’ll be just as happy with a disciplined life as we were if continued to
be lazy and comfortable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-notes" /><category term="self-help" /><summary type="html">Spartan Discipline By Dominic Mann. This book can be found here. Mann gives tips, tricks, suggestions and analogies from Spartan’s lifestyle to illustrate how to develop self-discipline and be productive in our lives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Using google Hangouts video call from android</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/04/09/using-hangouts-video-call-android.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using google Hangouts video call from android" /><published>2020-04-09T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-04-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/04/09/using-hangouts-video-call-android</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/04/09/using-hangouts-video-call-android.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog shows step-by-step process on using Google’s Hangouts apps to do video
calls from your android device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1-install-googles-hangouts-app-from-playstore&quot;&gt;Step 1. Install Google’s Hangouts app from playstore&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/google-hangouts-tutorial/01-install-google-hangouts.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Install Google Hangouts app&quot; /&gt;
This is needed for you join the video call later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2-install-googles-hangouts-meet-app-from-playstore&quot;&gt;Step 2. Install Google’s Hangouts Meet app from playstore&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/google-hangouts-tutorial/02-install-google-hangouts-meet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Install Google Hangouts Meet app&quot; /&gt;
Note that both ‘Hangouts’ as well as ‘Hangouts Meet’ are required to
successfully join the video call!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3-open-hangouts-meet-app&quot;&gt;Step 3. Open Hangouts Meet app&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/google-hangouts-tutorial/03-open-meet-app.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Open Hangouts Meet app&quot; /&gt;
If you calendar has already been updated, an event will show up at the bottom.
Tap on the ‘Join’ button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-4-join-the-video-call&quot;&gt;Step 4. Join the video call&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/google-hangouts-tutorial/04-join-the-video-call.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Join video call&quot; /&gt;
The previous step will start the ‘Hangouts’ app. In here, tap on the
‘JOIN VIDEO CALL’ button at the bottom of your screen to join your video call.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="tutorial" /><summary type="html">Introduction This blog shows step-by-step process on using Google’s Hangouts apps to do video calls from your android device.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Relaxation Response</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/04/06/relaxation-response.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Relaxation Response" /><published>2020-04-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-04-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/04/06/relaxation-response</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/04/06/relaxation-response.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-relaxation-response&quot;&gt;The Relaxation Response&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Dr. Herbert Benson. This book can be found
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Relaxation-Response-Herbert-Benson/dp/0380006766&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
In this book, Dr. Benson writes about a response that is opposite to
“fight or flight” response, which is called relaxation response (RR). He lists
the benefits of this response and simple steps to elicit this response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Field of medicine can be construed as a 3-legged sturdy stool
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;medications&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;surgery and similar medical procedures&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;self-care&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;belief is potentially central to our health&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;remembered wellness (aka placebo effect) also elicits RR&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 step process in the mind/body technique:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;elicit RR to quiet the mind&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;after the mind has become quiet rewire the thoughts and actions in the
desired direction&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have a balanced approach to all 3 of the legs of this stool. When in doubt,
do consult your physician&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;technology instead of easing our lives has only resulted in more stress&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we are frustrated that we can’t even solve simple problems like being on time,
due to congestion. Thus we become victims of stress.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stress not only affects us mentally, but also physically.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;hypertension is currently a worldwide phenomenon as well as an epidemic.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;It is caused by
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;bad diet&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;lack of exercise&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;family disposition&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;environmental stress&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;all animals respond to chronic stressful conditions via the
“fight or flight” response (needed for survival)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;situations that demand we adjust our behavior elicit this response&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;this response involves increased BP, shallow breath, increased heart rate.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;this response needs to be used, for eg, running away from or fighting with
the enemy. If it is not used, over periods of time, it can lead to
disastrous consequences, which is what is happening nowadays.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the opposite of “fight or flight” response is the RR
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it reverses the adverse effects of “fight or flight” response&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;evoking RR is to be done via these steps
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;a quiet environment&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;a mental device (a word, phrase or mantra) that should be repeated. This
repetition helps avoid distracting thoughts&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;a passive attitude (by disregarding other thoughts and returning to the
mental device in case of any distraction). This is one of the key things
to elicit RR!&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;a comfortable position&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the above process is also known as Transcendental Meditation, a refined yoga
practice developed by Maharishi Mahesh Yogi&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the risk of developing atherosclerosis is directly related to the BP as well
as cholesterol levels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HBP directly affects 3 organs: heart, brain and kidneys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;events which require adjusting of our behavior cause stress in us. A stressful
person is more susceptible to diseases and having more BP&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we simply cannot deal with the complexities the life throws at us. So, better
to learn effective ways to cope with those&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it has been shown now that through voluntary mental acts, one can control the
“involuntary” bodily mechanisms like BP, heart-rate, oxygen consumption,
(aka metabolism) etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;alpha waves are the brain waves which indicate the feeling of well-being&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;major physiologic change due to meditation is the decrease in metabolism
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;aka hypometabolism&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;only 3 things cause this: meditation, sleep or hibernation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;hibernation is shows a drop in rectal temperatures, meditation doesn’t&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;sleep and meditation
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;in sleep metabolism decreases gradually until 4-5 hrs&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;in meditation it decreases rapidly in the first 2-3 mins&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;meditation increases alpha waves in brain&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;meditation decreases blood lactate content (associated with anxiety)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;thus meditation and sleep can’t be substituted for one another!&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;altered state of consciousness
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;RR is associated with this state&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it is one of the states in between coma -&amp;gt; sleep -&amp;gt; drowsiness -&amp;gt; alert -&amp;gt; hyper-alert&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;this state needs to be purposefully evoked&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;people going psychoanalysis sessions will find it hard to assume passive
attitude, thus difficult for them to elicit RR&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;excessive daily elicitation of RR can lead to hallucinations due to sensory
deprivation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;within few weeks of stopping RR, our body typically goes back to its original
state, so better to be regular with this process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-notes" /><category term="self-help" /><summary type="html">The Relaxation Response By Dr. Herbert Benson. This book can be found here. In this book, Dr. Benson writes about a response that is opposite to “fight or flight” response, which is called relaxation response (RR). He lists the benefits of this response and simple steps to elicit this response.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Never Split the Difference</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/03/10/never-split-the-difference.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Never Split the Difference" /><published>2020-03-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-03-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/03/10/never-split-the-difference</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/03/10/never-split-the-difference.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;never-split-the-difference&quot;&gt;Never Split the Difference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Christopher Voss. This book can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Never-Split-Difference-Negotiating-Depended/dp/0062407805&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
Voss talks about how some of the inter-personal skills like active-listening,
empathy, mirroring and calibrated questions can take you a long way when it
comes to negotiation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;listening is the most active way to show empathy towards fellow human beings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;negotiation has 2 parts
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;information gathering&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;behavior influencing&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in all situations, both parties involved want something from the other. The
aim then is to get what one wants without inflicting damage onto the other
party. In this world, you get what you ask for. So ask correctly!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to successfully negotiate one needs to prepare first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;assumptions-blind-us-hypotheses-guide-us&quot;&gt;assumptions blind us, hypotheses guide us&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;most of us go to a negotiation with a list of points to argue. When we are
talking we are putting those points across and when we are not talking we
are thinking about our next points!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one really strong way to avoid this is to divert the full attention to what
your counterpart has to say. This is active listening. This will disarm
them, making the voice in their head to quiet down.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the goal is to understand what they really need. Easiest way to achieve this
is to have them talk more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;slow-it-down&quot;&gt;slow it down&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;don’t be the problem solver, be the people mover&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if we come out as being in a hurry, might loose trust of our counterparts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;slowing it down can also help in calming the situation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tonal modulation also plays an important role here
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;late night FM DJ voice can soothe your counterpart while driving the point
across, without any escalations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;playful, calm, relaxed voice with a conscious smile - should be your
default voice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;assertive tone - to be used rarely. It can trigger pushback.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mirroring&quot;&gt;mirroring&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a form of imitation, whereby we copy each other in order to comfort each
other&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tone, behaviour, body language, words, speech can all be mirrored&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this sends out an unconscious signal to the other that we are connected&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;being right is not the key in a successful negotiation, but having the right
mindset is&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;confronting a pitbull will only lead to a messy scene. There’s a better way:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;use the late night FM DJ voice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;start with “I’m sorry”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;mirroring&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;silence (to let the mirroring do its magic)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;language of negotiation is the one of quickly building a rapport with the
other party for subsequent discussions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tactical-empathy&quot;&gt;tactical empathy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;really understand your audience’s emotions and feelings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;making a commitment to understand their world&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and also hearing what’s behind those feelings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is a really great tool to maximize neural resonance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dont-feel-their-pain-label-it&quot;&gt;don’t feel their pain, label it&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how can we separate people from their problem, when their emotions are the
problem!?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emotions are the main reason for derailment of communication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;once people get upset at each other, rational thinking disappears&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identify and label the emotions. Talk about them. Influence the emotions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;labelling
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;acknowledge the other party’s emotions and label it&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it gets you closer to them without really asking any external questions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;labelling an emotion disrupts it’s effect on our brains and makes us think
rationally about those emotions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;labels almost always begin with “it seems like”, “it sounds like”, etc&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;emotions have 2 layers in every person:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;presenting behavior&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;underlying cause&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a good negotiator uses labelling in order to get to the former&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;use labelling to diffuse negative emotions and reinforce the positive ones&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;at first do an “accusation audit”: label and list all negative things the
counterpart would say as a response&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;other party has all the more barriers to deny your request than to agree to
them. So always try to deny/remove those barriers from the discussion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the quicker you deny the role of amygdala in your counterpart’s brain, the
faster you can gain their trust&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;no-is-the-start-of-the-negotiation&quot;&gt;no is the start of the negotiation!&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 types of yes:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;counterfeit - said as an escape route&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;confirmation - innocent yes to a black/white question&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;commitment - real deal!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 types of primary urges in every one of us:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;need to feel safe and secure&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;need to feel in control of things&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allowing them the option to say no, can give them sense of being in control&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;once they feel safe and in control, they quickly jump into finding actions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;embrace no!
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;because if you can’t cope with a no, then you can’t be a good negotiator&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if the other party is not listening to you then one option to make them is
to antagonise them by asking a question whose answer is a clear no.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 sweet words in any negotiation are: that’s right!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in order to influence behavior, we need the following stages:
(behavioral change stairway model)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;active listening&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;empathy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;rapport&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;behavioral change&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“you’re right” is the worst word for a negotiator!
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it means that they agree that YOU are right&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;but they haven’t owned those thoughts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;so it’s hard to get a behavioral change from this point on&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;everyone of us has the urge to feel to be heard and understood. So, always
create an unconditional positive regard for the party, just like how a
psychologist does for his patients&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use summary (paraphrasing + labelling) to drive out “that’s right”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;time&quot;&gt;time&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we should always uncover the other party’s hidden motives and irrational
thoughts. Then, use those to bend their reality and also gain leverage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;compromise (splitting the difference) is always seen to be a moral good and a
win-win situation. It is not! In fact, no deal is better than bad deal!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we compromise because it is easy and feels safe.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;so, never split the difference!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make time your ally
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;other party’s insistence on deadline is only going to make you take
irrational decisions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;because we always rush for deadline&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;and that’s because of the perceived consequences of not meeting the deadline&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;deadlines are almost always arbitrary and can be flexible&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;deadlines are thus the boogeyman of negotiations!&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;however, do not keep your deadlines secret from the other party, as it can
only lead to impasse. Because, they will continue to wait for a better deal
from you! So you’re effectively negotiating with yourself!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fairness&quot;&gt;fairness&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if you go to any negotiation thinking that the other party also thinks like
you, that is just wrong. It is not empathy, it is projection.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;even if we guide our decision making using rational thoughts, the actual
decision making is done via emotions! So, ignoring the role of our emotions in
decision making is only to our own peril.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we can become very irrational under the percieved notion of unfairness against
us. This can also be a significant motivator for us.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thus, use the “fair” word very cautiously. Of the 3 ways of using it, only one
is right:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“we just want what’s fair for all of us” - form of implicit accusation.
Immediately triggers defensive behavior in them. If we recieve such an
accusation, we should just apologize and request for a start over from where
they felt it was unfair.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“we’ve given you a fair offer” - nefarious jab on the opponents. If we
recieve such a statement, mirror it, followed by a labelling to try them
show how it is fair.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“I want you to feel fair at all times. So stop me whenever you feel it is
being unfair to you and we’ll address it” - positive usage. Sets up am image
of you as a honest negotiator. Since as a negotiator, you should be seen as
being fair.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bend-their-reality&quot;&gt;bend their reality&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;figure out their emotional drivers and then bend their reality from an insult
into a victory. (eg: a babysitter provides a peaceful evening)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prospect theory
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;certainty effect - people are drawn to sure things rather than probability,
even when the latter is a better choice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;loss aversion - people will take greater risks to avoid losses than to
achieve gains&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;anchor and adjustment effect - when the seller inflates the price and then
gives us a “huge” discount&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;reciprocity effect - when you gift someone they feel the need to reciprocate
in kind&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thus, in a negotiation, show them how much they’ll loose if the deal doesn’t
come through
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;anchor their emotions by using accusation audit. Then play it on their loss
aversion&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;let them go first, most of the times. Let the other side anchor monetary
negotiations first. But be careful about the anchor and adjustment effect
here!&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;allude to a range in case you have to got first. Now if you offer a range,
expect them to come in at the lower range :)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;pivot to non-monetary terms - show them other benefits apart from money.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;when you do talk about money use odd numbers. Eg: using numbers ending with
zeros means you are inviting for negotiations. A number like 4751 sounds
like a permanent number based on thought.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;surprise with an unexpected gift - give them an extreme anchor and then
throw a gift. This anchors on reciprocity effect&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to negotiate a better salary
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;be pleasantly persistent on non-monetary terms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;salary terms without success terms is a Russian roulette - after salary
negotiation define metrics for success and salary raise for future&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;spark their interest in your success and gain an unofficial mentor. Eg: by
asking in an interview, what does it take to be successful here?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;calibrated-questions&quot;&gt;Calibrated questions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;negotiation is
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;coaxing not overcoming&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;coopting not defeating&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;giving them the illusion of control&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;carefully calibrated open-ended question
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it’s typically a “how” question&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it’s an ask for help&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it invites them to solve your problem&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it thus gives them an illusion of control&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it converts a confrontational showdown into a joint problem solving session&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;calibrate your questions
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;avoid: can, is, do, does. These are close-ended and there’s nothing much for
the other party to interpret.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;use reporter’s questions: who, what, when, where, how.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;don’t use why often. It can be offensive.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we will have to regulate our emotions all throughout this process, if we want
to keep our hopes of getting what we want
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;bite your tongue, as in, pause to dissipate your emotions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;collect your thoughts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;if you’re verbally assaulted, pause and counter it using a carefully
calibrated question&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;negotiators are the design architects to get a verbal agreement and then to
also get it executed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rule-of-3-for-getting-execution-done&quot;&gt;rule of 3 for getting execution done&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;yes is nothing without a how
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“how am I supposed to do that?” is a really good calibrated question&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it is a gentle but firm way of saying no&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it also buys you time to think and regroup&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it is a way to help convince them that it was their solution&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;once they have given a solution, summarise it back and try to get a
“that’s right” from them&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you should beware of the parties behind the negotiating table.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;some of them can have the ability to derail the agreement&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;some of them can also be the ones who’ll finally implement those&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;so asking “what does your team or colleagues see challenges in this area”
is very helpful&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;it takes only one bit-player to screw up the deal&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in any negotiation, being aware of their mental state via verbal,
para-verbal and non-verbal cues is very critical
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;assertive calibrated questions are an effective way to deal with jerks,
instead of going brute force&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7-38-55 rule
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;only 7% of the message is based on words&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;38% comes from tone of your voice&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;55% from body language&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;in case their sayings are not congruent, label their emotions in order
to unmask the real reason&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rule of three
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;3 kinds of yes: commitment, confirmation and counterfeit&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;trying to get them to agree to your terms 3 times&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;after first agreement, summarise the whole thing to get a “that’s right”
and finally ask calibrated questions like “what to do if things go off
 track” to get them to agree once more. Each time, try to spot any
 incongruous behavior&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pinocchio effect
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on an average liars use more words and more third party nouns (him,
then, they, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;they want to distance themselves from the lies&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;look at the use of pronouns
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;pay attention to their use of pronouns&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the more they use I, me, etc the less important they are&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the harder it is to get a first person pronoun out of them, the more
important they are&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chris discount
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;naming yourself creates forced empathy and makes them see you as human&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;introduce and humanize yourself, in a friendly way&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;humor and humanity are the best way to break ice&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to get them to bid against themselves
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;learn to say no but without actually saying it.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;“how am I supposed to do that”&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;“I’m sorry, your offer is generous but I can’t do that”&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;“I’m sorry, I can’t do that”&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;“I’m sorry, no”&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;use downward deflection during delivery&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bargaining&quot;&gt;bargaining&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;don’t shop for groceries when you’re hungry!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;any response that is not outright rejection of your offer means you’ve the
upper hand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 types of people
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;accomodators&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;assertive&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;data loving analysts&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to be effective at bargaining, you need a combination of all these 3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to be good, learn to be yourself at the bargaining table&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to be great, you’ve to add to your strengths&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;analyst
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;methodological and diligent&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;no worries about time&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;their image is important to them&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;rarely disclose their emotion&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;they hate surprises&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;they loose trust quickly&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;they are skeptical&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;give them a chance to think first&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;accomodators
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;as long as they are communicating they are happy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;they love the win-win&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;very easy to talk to&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;extremely friendly&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;listen to their ideas&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;be sure to talk about the implementation details before&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;assertive
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;time is money&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;love winning often at the expense of others&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;have aggressive communication style&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;wants to be heard&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;they focus on their own goals&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;they take more but give very less&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;you must listen to them first&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;mirrors are very effective of these people&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;strive to get a “that’s right” from these&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;why we fail to figure their type
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;because of the “I’m normal paradox”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;we try to project our thinking onto other people&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;that’s a disastrous thing in a negotiation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;everbody has a plan until they get hit in the mouth
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;always invite them to lead with the number first&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;when you receive it, deflect this “punch” to open up them&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;effective-ways-to-assert-smartly&quot;&gt;effective ways to assert smartly&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;don’t put the anger out on the person. Instead, take a deep breath and deflect
it on the proposal itself. this is called strategic umbridge. AKA offense
taking with poise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;why question makes others defensive. One case where it is useful for us is
when we want them to defend for us. Eg: why would you choose to leave our
existing products and services and choose our competitors?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;choose “I” using cool and level readme way&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;never be needy for a deal (be ready to walk away)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;always express yourself calmly but firmly and in an emphathetic way.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aggression and anger will only trigger violence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;focus on the issue not on the counterpart.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never create an enemy. Punching back should always be the last resort&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ackermann model (haggling system)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;set your target price&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;first offer should be a 65% of the target price&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;calculate 3 raises of 85, 95 and 100%&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;use lots of empathy and different ways of saying no to get where you want to go&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;use precise non-round numbers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;throw a non-monetary thing on the final amount to say that this is your limit&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;find-the-black-swan&quot;&gt;find the black swan&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;these are the unknown-unknowns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;these can be game changers in negotiation dynamics as they give us leverage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;black swans can’t be predicted with the existing set of norms. They are
typically beyond these&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if bits and pieces of a scenario don’t add up, then probably our framework of
expectations are off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we must have our known-knowns guide us, not blind us for what we don’t know&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;always have the beginner’s view&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;unearthing of black swans requires a change in our mindset. Look at nuances in
our counterparts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make them believe that they have the loss of the deal doesn’t come through,
then you have the leverage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 types of leverage
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;positive
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;ability or power we have when they express their desires/wants.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;we can either fulfill them or deny&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;many times, by making offers sooner we give up our leverage&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;negative
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;the most common type that we know of&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;these typically threats to destroy things we value&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;this plays on our aversion to loss&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;be careful as these are very difficult to clean up. If you really want to
do this, try labelling it.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;this is because of the paradox of power - the harder we push We likely
will get harder resistance&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;normative
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;showing differences in their norms/beliefs and actions&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;no one wants to look like a hippocrite&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;understanding the opponent and what they want almost always gives us
leverage. For this, you must listen to them intently.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;similarity principle
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;we trust those who are similar to us&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;belonging is our animalistic instinct&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;similarity trigger rapport&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;without understanding them, there’s no way to know their dynamics, thereby
gaining leverage on them&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;moments like “they’re crazy” are the right places where we need to figure
out the black swans.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Some of the mistakes behind such “crazy” moments:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;they’re ill-informed - because people acting based on incomplete info
might sound crazy to those with some other info&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;they’re constrained - and so they might not be upcoming about it&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;they’ve other interests - presence of hidden interests&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some ways to unearth black swans
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;get facetime - very critical (7-38-55 rule!)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;observe during unguarded moments - mostly just before start and after end of
meetings&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;when it doesn’t make any sense, there’s cents to be made!&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it’s not the people we are afraid of, it’s the conflict&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;embrace the regular thoughtful approach to negotiation and conflict resolution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;remember that the adversary is the situation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;negotiation-one-sheet&quot;&gt;negotiation one-sheet&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the goal
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;typically represents the best case&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;but you should have thought about worst too&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;also be flexible towards these&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;set an optimistic but clear goal&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;write the goal&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;carry the written goal&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;summary
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;get on the same page from the onset&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;get a that’s right from them after summarising&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;labels and accusation audit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;calibrated questions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;non-cash offers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-notes" /><category term="self-help" /><summary type="html">Never Split the Difference By Christopher Voss. This book can be found here. Voss talks about how some of the inter-personal skills like active-listening, empathy, mirroring and calibrated questions can take you a long way when it comes to negotiation!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Drop your tools - Does Expertise have a dark side?</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/01/18/drop-your-tools.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Drop your tools - Does Expertise have a dark side?" /><published>2020-01-18T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-01-18T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/01/18/drop-your-tools</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2020/01/18/drop-your-tools.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my notes after watching Dr. Sean Brady’s Keynote talk at LCA-2020. The full
recorded video can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Yv4tI6939q0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expertise is certainly necessary for us to be better at our jobs and do less
mistakes. However, there are cases when expertise can &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Negative_priming&quot;&gt;negatively prime&lt;/a&gt;
us down the wrong solution path! He uses the examples of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/1978/01/19/archives/new-jersey-pages-coliseum-roof-collapses-at-hartford-civic-center.html&quot;&gt;Hartford convention center collapse&lt;/a&gt;
and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mann_Gulch_fire&quot;&gt;Mann Gulch wildfire&lt;/a&gt; to
show that in the moments of pressure we continue to cling onto our expertise
despite of all the warning signs to the contrary. In some scenarios, our
expertise itself can be the greatest source of negative priming since we use it
sub-consciously (and automatically) at all times!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we end up trying to solve a problem that’s slightly outside our expertise,
even if we know that our “tools” aren’t giving us the right solution, we continue
to hold onto them (just like the firefighters of Mann Gulch did)! It is hard for
all of us to accept the fact that the tools we currently use are not the right
ones for the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some nice quotes from this talk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“The greatest obstacle to knowledge is not ignorance. It is the illusion of knowledge”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“We all see the world with the prism of our expertise”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“In pursuit of knowledge, everyday something is acquired. In the pursuit of wisdom, everyday something is dropped”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="psychology" /><summary type="html">Introduction This is my notes after watching Dr. Sean Brady’s Keynote talk at LCA-2020. The full recorded video can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">RAPIDS ML dev setup</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/12/18/rapids-ml-dev-setup.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RAPIDS ML dev setup" /><published>2019-12-18T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-12-18T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/12/18/rapids-ml-dev-setup</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/12/18/rapids-ml-dev-setup.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post is an attempt to simplify the process of setting up of an
environment for &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rapidsai/cuml&quot;&gt;cuML&lt;/a&gt; development. If your
environment already has docker and you have access to building images and
running containers using them, then the Dockerfile shipped with cuML repo is the
easiest way to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pre-reqs&quot;&gt;Pre-reqs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.nvidia.com/cuda-downloads&quot;&gt;cuda toolkit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download the bash script from the github gist &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/teju85/51ff12886f5ae9967a4cab6fd0376953&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and save it as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rapids-setup&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;~10-15GB of free disk-space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;instructions&quot;&gt;Instructions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run the bash script to install cuML and its dependencies. Recommended approach
is to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.anaconda.com/&quot;&gt;anaconda&lt;/a&gt;. This script installs all the
needed dependencies in a stand-alone folder and thus does not need root access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;bash ./rapids-setup installCuml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end, it prints a couple of environment variables to be set in your bash
terminal. Execute them and you should now be ready to run tests and develop!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="cuda" /><category term="rapids" /><category term="cuml" /><summary type="html">Introduction This blog post is an attempt to simplify the process of setting up of an environment for cuML development. If your environment already has docker and you have access to building images and running containers using them, then the Dockerfile shipped with cuML repo is the easiest way to get started.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Teditor v1.6.0</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/11/30/teditor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Teditor v1.6.0" /><published>2019-11-30T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-11-30T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/11/30/teditor</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/11/30/teditor.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;teditor-v160&quot;&gt;Teditor v1.6.0!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glad to announce the release of the next version of teditor: v1.6.0. It
can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/teju85/teditor/releases/tag/1.6.0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;changelog&quot;&gt;Changelog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changes/features in this release:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;grep mode&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for working with remote files&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simplified indent/unindent logic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;File history storage syntax update in light of remote file syntax&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enabled keep-lines/remove-lines command and also their undo/redo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alert users about working on remote buffers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Case insensitive searching via a rc option&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Various fixes to improve perf on remote buffers (eg: usage of DirCache)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Various bug fixes and addition of utility methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;grep-mode&quot;&gt;grep mode&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is similar to the grep mode in emacs. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;M-x grep &amp;lt;enter&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; type the regex
to search for and the file/dir where to search and then press enter. This should
open a buffer with all grep results highlighted. From then onwards, pressing
enter on each result of grep will take you to that file and line (similar to
what happens in grep mode of emacs).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="teditor" /><summary type="html">Teditor v1.6.0! Glad to announce the release of the next version of teditor: v1.6.0. It can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Teditor v1.5.0</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/11/19/teditor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Teditor v1.5.0" /><published>2019-11-19T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-11-19T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/11/19/teditor</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/11/19/teditor.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;teditor-v150&quot;&gt;Teditor v1.5.0!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glad to announce the release of the next version of teditor: v1.5.0. It
can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/teju85/teditor/releases/tag/1.5.0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;changelog&quot;&gt;Changelog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changes/features in this release:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brand new Option interface to customize editor behavior via rc-file&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Revamp of commandline parsing to print help message, pass rc-file, etc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Track version info from the commandline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bug fixes to removeRegion functionality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support in dir-mode for opening remote directories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reorg of cmds and modes source files to something more aptly named locations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;commandline-options&quot;&gt;Commandline options&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From now onwards, commandline options for the editor are documented and can be
accessed via the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;teditor &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;customizing-editor-via-rc-files&quot;&gt;Customizing editor via rc files&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easiest way is to create a fresh rc file via the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-dump&lt;/code&gt; option and then edit
it to customize as per your needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;teditor &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;-dump&lt;/span&gt; /path/to/rc/file
&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# open and edit this file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="teditor" /><summary type="html">Teditor v1.5.0! Glad to announce the release of the next version of teditor: v1.5.0. It can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Teditor v1.4.0</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/11/18/teditor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Teditor v1.4.0" /><published>2019-11-18T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-11-18T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/11/18/teditor</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/11/18/teditor.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;teditor-v140&quot;&gt;Teditor v1.4.0!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glad to announce the release of the next version of teditor: v1.4.0. It
can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/teju85/teditor/releases/tag/1.4.0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;changelog&quot;&gt;Changelog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changes/features in this release:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Complete removal of multiple-cursors from the editor. (reason below)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bug fixes to highlighting the empty lines under selection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-no-multiple-cursors&quot;&gt;Why no Multiple Cursors?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are multiple reasons for this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We’ll introduce more macro-like interface that’ll void the need for such a
thing. Many blogs have been written about this &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@schtoeffel/you-don-t-need-more-than-one-cursor-in-vim-2c44117d51db&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://nullprogram.com/blog/2017/09/07/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Thus I do not want to
elaborate further on this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In future, underlying implementation of buffers can be optimized very easily
without multiple-cursors support &lt;a href=&quot;https://nullprogram.com/blog/2017/09/07/&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="teditor" /><summary type="html">Teditor v1.4.0! Glad to announce the release of the next version of teditor: v1.4.0. It can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The subtle art of not giving a f**k</title><link href="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/11/13/subtle-art-of-not-giving-a-fk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The subtle art of not giving a f**k" /><published>2019-11-13T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-11-13T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/11/13/subtle-art-of-not-giving-a-fk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teju85.github.io/blog/2019/11/13/subtle-art-of-not-giving-a-fk.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-subtle-art-of-not-giving-a-fk&quot;&gt;The subtle art of not giving a f**k&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Mark Manson. This book can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Subtle-Art-Not-Giving-Counterintuitive/dp/0062457713&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
Mark talks about how to give our limited f**ks to only where they matter the most
and thereby showing us a way to leader happier lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;backwards law&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wanting positive experience is a negative experience; accepting negative experience is a positive experience.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everything worthwhile in life is won through surmounting the associated negative experience.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any attempt to escape the negative, to avoid it or quash it or silence it, only backfires.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The avoidance of suffering is a form of suffering.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The avoidance of struggle is a struggle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The denial of failure is a failure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hiding what is shameful is itself a form of shame.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not giving a fuck doesn’t mean being indifferent, it means being comfortable with being different.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to not give a fuck about adversity, one must first have something more important than this adversity to give a fuck about.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;maturity is what happens when you decide to give a fuck to only things that are fuckworthy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the only way to overcome pain is first to learn how to bear it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;happiness is not a solvable equation. Dissatisfaction, suffering and uneasiness are inherent parts of our lives.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there’s no life without problems. Thus, hope for a life with good problems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we find happiness by solving problems. Thus happiness is an action.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 main ways we fuck our lives are via: denial and victim-mentality.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;negative emotions mean a call to action. Positive ones are an indication of something done right. But that doesn’t mean the emotions are always correct. We should make a habit of questioning our emotions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;whatever makes us feel good will also inevitably make us feel bad.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nobody asks themselves “what pain do they want in their life? For what cause are they willing to struggle?”. The answer to this question is typically the determinant of one’s life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;solution to pain and suffering is the acceptance of it and not their denial.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who you are is defined by what you are willing to struggle for.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;true measurement of one’s self-worth is not based on how one feels about one’s positive experiences, but how they fell about their negative ones.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;under negative experiences, many folks become entitled: either they are special and everybody is stupid or everybody’s smart and they are stupid. In both cases they are the special ones.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;vast majority of life is unextraordinary. However, media always bombards us with those exceptional ones (good or bad) only. This leads to entitlement issues.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;people become exceptional because they are obsessed with improvement and beacuse they believe that they are not that great currently. It is actually anti-entitlement!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;living a normal life, making friends, reading a good book, spending time with your family. These are all ordinary things. But maybe they are ordinary beacuse these are the ones we actually want.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;self-awareness is like an onion. The more you peel the more you start crying at inappropriate times.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we control what our problems mean by choosing the standard we use to measure them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we will eventually compare ourselves with others. So, the real question is by what standard are we going to compare ourselves to others and also what values to use to set this standard?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the following values create really poor problems for people:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;pleasure&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;material success&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;always being right&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;always staying positive&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;because these things are really just the side effects of having good values. They by themselves are just empty highs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set good values/metrics for yourselves. This helps you give fucks only where it matters. Thus in turn gets you to a state of well-being whose side effects are happiness, pleasure and success.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;depending upon whether we chose the problems or it was forced down upon us, we will feel empowered or miserable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we cannot control what happens to us. But we can always control how we interpret it and respond to it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;accepting responsibility for our problems is the first step in solving them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we are responsible for experiences which are not our fault at all. This is life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no one else is responsible for your situation but you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fault is past tense. Responsibility is present and future tense.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;others can be blamed for how we feel, but they can’t be held responsible for how we feel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;growth is an endlessly iterative process. When we learn something new, we go from wrong to slightly less wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;analogy to ML!
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;our values are optimisation functions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;our actions = fwd prop&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;resulting emotions and thoughts = bwd prop&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;life itself = weights to be optimised&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nothing is certain until it has already happened and even then it’s debatable. So, certainty is enemy of growth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all beliefs are wrong. Some are just less wrong than others.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;remember how the telephone game works? (whisper what you heard into next person’s ears) our memories are just like that!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our beliefs are malleable and our memories are horribly unreliable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;uncertainty removes the need to judge others (as well as ourselves!) and to have biased views.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;unless we are uncertain about how successful we’ll be, we won’t be able to strive towards it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the openness to being wrong must exist in order for us to grow or change ourselves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Manson’s law of avoidance: the more something threatens your identity, the more you’ll avoid it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how to breed a little uncertainty in us:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;what if I’m wrong?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;what would it mean if I were wrong?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;would being wrong create a better or worse problem than the current one for myself and others?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;as kids we fall many times while trying to walk. But we just get up and try again. However, as adults we somehow end up learning to avoid failures!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if someone is better than us at something, then he has failed at it more times than we are.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if we are unwilling to fail then we’ll also be unwilling to succeed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for many of us, our proudest moments come at the face of greatest adversity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rather than numbing it out, learn to withstand the pain you’ve chosen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;action isn’t just the effect of motivation, it’s also the cause of it. So always “do something”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;motivation-loop: inspiration -&amp;gt; motivation -&amp;gt; action -&amp;gt; inspiration …&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we are defined by what we choose to reject&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;part of becoming honest is to develop the ability to say and receive ‘no’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;acts of love are valid only if they’re performed unconditionally and without expectations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;without conflict there can be no trust&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;breadth helps realize what is worth your faculty. Depth is where the gold is buried. You’ve to commit yourself and dig deeper to find it. This applies to relationships, careers and life in general.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;death is the light by which the shadow of all of life’s meanings are measured&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;death is inevitable. If we come to terms with it, then we suddenly become free to choose greater values to measure ourselves against.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;without the acknowledge of the presence of death, superficial will seem important and important will seem superficial.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;death is the correct answer to all the important life questions we never dare asking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-notes" /><category term="self-help" /><summary type="html">The subtle art of not giving a f**k By Mark Manson. This book can be found here. Mark talks about how to give our limited f**ks to only where they matter the most and thereby showing us a way to leader happier lives.</summary></entry></feed>